好的，呃，是的，谢谢大家的到来。
Okay, uh, yeah, thanks for coming.
那我们现在开始吧，今天的内容。
Let's Let's get started, but today.
好的，那我们先回顾一下上节课的内容。
Yeah. Yeah, so let's do a recap of last lecture.
上节课我们讲了GPU，对吧，还有奥林匹克Coda。
So last lecture, we talk about GPUs, right, and Olympic Coda.
我们学到的是GPU的执行模型，我们知道GPU有线程层级结构，
So what we learned is the GPU execution model, where we know GPU has thread hierarchy,
从网格到块再到线程。
from grade to block to threads.
当你编写GPO代码时，我们称之为GPO内核，我们
And when you write the GPO code, we call it a GPO kernel and the way we
基本上写的代码就是通过这个线程层级结构，把内核启动到很多很多线程上。
basically write that code is basically we launch that kernel to many many threads through this,
呃，就是通过线程层级结构，好吗？
uh thread hierarchy, okay?
我们还知道GPU有独立于主机内存的地址空间。
And we know GPU has a distinct address space compared to the host memory,
我们称之为GPU内存，或者设备内存，或者HBM，高带宽内存。
and we call that GPU memory or device memory or HBM, high bandwidth memory.
为了让你的程序访问这部分内存，
And in order for your program to access this part of memory,
CUDA为你提供了一些API，比如像cudaMemcpy这样的函数。
Coda provides you some APS, like Mock Coda memo copy, something like that. Okay.
还记得pin memory的定义吗？pin memory是
And there's still remember the definition of pin memory, pin memory is a part of
为GPU保留的主机内存的一部分。
the host memory that is reserved for GPUs.
在GPU内部，除了HBM之外，我们还有其他的内存层次结构
On the inside of GPO, besides the HBM, we also have other memory hierarchy built
集成在GPU本身内部。
into the GPO itself.
我们有每个线程的私有内存。
We have per thread, private memory.
例如，当我们编写GPU内核时，如果我们需要临时变量，
For example, when we write a GPO kernel, when we try to ask for temporal variable,
这个变量基本上就是在线程本地内存中创建的。
that variable was basically created in thread local memory.
我们有每个块的内存，我们称之为SRAM，对吧？
And we have per block memory, which we call SRAM, right?
一个块中的所有线程都可以访问这块内存。
All the threads in one block can access memory.
我们访问这块内存的方式是使用前缀shared，下划线shared，好吗？
And the way we access that memory is we use prefix called shared, under square shared, okay?
就像我说的，我们有HBM，也就是全局设备级别的内存。
And like I said, we have HBM, which is the global device level memory.
我们还简单介绍了两种同步原语。
And we also touch base on two synchronization primitives.
一种是CPU和GPU之间的同步。
One is the synchronization between CPU and GPU.
另一种是同一个块中所有线程之间的同步，好吗？
The other is the synchronization between all the threads in one block, okay?
我们还完成了第一个GPU程序，就是窗口平均或者等价的一维卷积，好吗？
And we also finish our first GPU program, which is the Window average or equivalent com one D, okay?
很好。那么今天的学习目标是，我们要在GPU上深入学习矩阵乘法。
Cool. Okay. Today's learning goal, we are going to grind the math mo on GPU.
我们大概会用半节课的时间来讲这个内容。
We'll probably spend half of the class on that.
那么我们基本上完成了GPU编程课程。
Then we basically finish our GPU programming class.
好的。接下来我们要讨论一些其他可以让算子更快的方法，
Okay. And we're going to talk about how we can there are some other alternative methods
其实主要就是编译器。
to make operator faster, which is basically compiler.
所以我们会稍微讲一下编译器，好吗？
So we are going to talk about compiler a little bit, okay.
嗯，是的。如果时间允许的话，我们基本上会总结一下这个算子增强层，
Um, yeah. And if time permits, we are going to basically wrap up this operator augmentation layer,
然后我们会涉及到另一个层次，就是图增强。
and we are going to touch another layer which is graph ogenation.
很好。那么在我们深入讲解Koda编程之前，我们要尝试
Cool. Okay. So before we get deep into Koda programming on met, we try to basically, uh,
改变你平时的编程方式，对吧？
change your way your normal way of programming, right?
所以在我们开始写Koda代码之前，需要做一些准备。
So before we try to program some Koda, we need to do a few things.
你需要把你的思维方式转变成SIMD模式，因为Koda是SMD。
So you need to convert your brain to SIMD because Koda is SMD.
好的。所以每当我给你一个操作符，并让你写一个Koda时，
Okay. So whenever I give you say operator and I ask you to write a Koda,
你应该考虑三个步骤。
you should think about three steps.
第一步，你需要识别可以并行执行的工作，对吧？
The first one is you should identify the work that can be performed in parallel, right?
然后你对工作进行划分。
And then you partition the work.
同时你还需要对与工作相关的数据进行划分，对吧？
And also you need to partition the data associated with our work, right?
接着你将工作划分和数据划分映射到Koda线程上，对吧？
And then you map the partition and the data partition to Koda thread, right?
然后你在那个oda内核中实现逻辑。
And you implement the logic in that oda kernel.
GPU基本上会把你的代码启动到很多很多线程上，明白吗？
And GPU will basically launch your code onto many many threads, okay?
这就是你在编写Coda程序时的思考方式。
That's the way how you think when you program Coda.
而为了让这个程序运行得更快，
And in order to make this program fast,
我希望你们还记得上节课我们是如何改进CdI编程以适应CD的，对吧？
I hope you still remember how we improve our CdI programming for the C D last class, right?
首先，我们需要确保对GPU进行超额订阅。
So first, we need to make sure we oversubscribe the GPUs.
我们要创建大量的分区任务，并尝试将它们全部
We create a lot of partition work, and we try to push all of them
推送到GPU有限数量的块中，
into the limited number of blocks on GPU,
这就叫做超额订阅。
That is called oversubscription.
我们还需要减少拖慢进度的线程。
We also need to mitigate stragglers.
我们希望尽量将工作负载分配得均等一些。
We don't want to we want to part workload as equal as possible.
这样每个线程大致能获得相同的工作量，对吧？
So every thread roughly get the same workload, right?
所以我们不想写那种ELs代码，因为那样有些线程会有工作，
So we don't want to write those kind of ELs, right, because some thread will get work,
而其他线程却没有，对吧？
but other threads are not, okay?
我们需要尽量减少通信。
And we need to minimize communication.
这里的通信指的是我们需要尽量减少内存层级之间的数据移动。
And here, communication means we need to minimize the data movement between memory hierarchies,
我们应该尽可能多地使用共享内存。
we should use the shared memory as much as possible.
明白了吗？但要遵守它们的约束条件，好吗？
Okay? But subject to their constraints, okay?
好的，那我们开始吧。
Cool. Then let's get started.
所以我们要做的是，S 等于 A，
So we're going to do this, right, S equals to A,
Mtmo B，这基本上让你看到 Mtmo 在做什么，对吧？
Mtmo B and this basically give you visualizing what is Mtmois doing, right?
然后我们按照我们的三个步骤来进行，好吗？
And let's follow our three steps, right?
我们先尝试找出可以并行执行的工作。
Let's try to first identify work that can be performed in parallel.
那么哪些工作是可以并行执行的呢？
So what is the work that can be performed in parallel?
所以基本上，每次我们可以取A的一行和B的一列，对吧？
So basically, every time we can grab a row on A and a column on B right and we
然后我们只需要对行和列做点积运算。
just do a dot product between row and columns.
所以我们基本上可以得到C中的一个结果元素，而所有这些行和列的乘积
So we basically can get one result entry in C, and all this row and column product
都可以并行完成。
can be done in parallel.
所以对于这个核函数，最直接的实现方式就是我们刚才描述的那样。
So the most straightforward implementation for this kernel is basically we do what I just described.
每个GPU线程取一行和一列，对吧？
Each GPU thread to grab one row and one column, right?
然后我们把它们分配到许多许多带有线程的块中去。
And then we launch them to many many blocks with threads.
好吗？为了编写这个核函数，呃，我们要做的是，
Okay? And in order to write that kernel, uh, what do we do is, we
基本上每个线程计算一个元素，最后我们得到了这个核函数。
basically each thread compte one element, and we ended up with this kernel.
请大家看一下，大概15秒钟。
And please look at that for maybe 15 seconds.
好的，是的，我们来试着过一遍。
Okay, yeah, let's try to go through it.
那这个是三，四，对吧？
So this one is three, four, right?
我们有一个矩阵，我们要有一个矩阵，这里的维度N大约是1024。
We have matrix we have to matrix which is the dimension N here N is roughly 1024.
我们接下来要申请几个块。
And we are going to ask for a few blocks.
这里我们申请的块的形状是32乘32，对吧？
Here we ask blocks of the shape of 32 by 32, right?
二维块，因为这个很简单，对吧？
Two dimensional blocks because this one is trivial, okay?
并且因为我们要让每个线程计算一个元素，所以总共，
And because we are going to let each thread to computer one element, so in total,
我们需要申请1024个线程。
we need to ask for 1024 threads.
这就是为什么每个块的线程数也是这个形状。好的。
That's why thread per block is also this shape. Okay.
这就是我们的核函数启动，对吧？
And this is our kernel launch, right?
这是CPU代码。我们让CPU启动内核到GPU上。
This is CPU code. We ask CPU to launch the kernel to GPS.
然后我们进入这个内核，嗯，我们要做的是使用block ID，
And then we go into this kernel, um, and what do we do is we use the block ID,
block D和thread ID来为每个线程获取索引。
block D and thread ID to get index for each thread.
在这里，我们让X负责A左矩阵的行，
Here, we let the X to take care of the row from the A left matrix,
并且我们用Y来索引B的列，对吧？
and we use Y to index the column of B, right?
然后我们要做的是为每个线程创建一个变量。
And then what do we do is we create one variable per thread.
所以这个变量会使用线程本地内存，
So this variable we'll use the the thread local memory,
对，因为我们没有使用共享前缀。
right, because we don't use the shared prefix.
所以这个会分配在线程本地内存上，本质上就是寄存器，好吗？
So this will be allocated on thread local memory, which is essentially registers, okay?
然后我们循环遍历这个维度，对吧？好的。
And then we loop over, we board this dimension, right? Okay.
我们要做的是取一个元素，把它们相加，
And what do we do is we will grab one element, it them together, and we
并把结果累加到这个结果里，对吧。
will accumulate results into this result, right.
最后我们让这个线程把结果写回
And eventually we this thread to write the result back into
我们的结果数组C。明白了吗？
our result array C. Okay? Makes sense, right?
基本上，我们启动K个线程，每个线程负责一个元素。
So basically, we launch one K threadach thread taking care of one element.
好的。那我们来分析一下内存，也就是IO，因为这是我们关心的。
Okay. Okay. So let's try to analyze the memory, the IO, right, because we care about that.
每个线程的全局内存访问量是
Okay. So the global memory rate per thread is
基本上每个线程需要读取一行和一列。
basically each thread need to read one row and one colom.
所以基本上是2N，对吧？
So it's basically two N, right?
那么有多少个线程呢，
So so how many threads,
我已经说过是unsquare线程，对吧？
I already said is unsquare threads, right?
因为那个线程应该对应于结果的形状，
Because that thread should be corresponding to the shape of the result,
也就是数组中的元素数量，对吗？
number of elements in the array, okay?
所以总的内存访问基本上是unsquare乘以二，对吧？
So the total memory access is essentially unsquare times two, right?
是立方。
Is cube.
好的，这意味着为了启动这个核函数，我们需要读取全局内存，
Okay, that means in order to launch this kerdle, we need to read the global memory,
从HBM读取内容到寄存器这么多次，对吗？
read the content from HBM to register this many times, okay?
那么有多少内存会使用线程本地内存？
And how many memory will use thread local memory?
基本上，我们每个线程只用一个float，对吧。
So basically, we only use one float per thread, right.
好的，这就是Mtmo核函数的基本版本。
Okay. That is the basic version of Mtmo kernel.
我希望你能明白这个，很直接。
I hope this makes sense to you, straightforward.
你知道我们接下来要做什么，对吧？
And you know what we are going to do next, right?
我们要改进这个，因为这个做得不好。
We are going to improve this because this one is not good.
根据我们上CPU MTM课时讲的内容，你知道，其实我们可以利用更多的内存，
According to the class we did for CPU MTM, you know, we can actually use more memory from
比如线程本地内存或者共享内存。
either thread local memory or from the shared memory.
我们还可以做分块，对吧？
And we can do telling, right.
所以我们要把分块应用到这个CPU内核上，好吗？
So we are going to apply telling to this CPU kernel, okay?
另一个直觉，我觉得我不用再重复了。
Another intuition, I don't think I need to repeat.
就是，通过观察这个，
That is, by looking at this,
P内存层次结构，我们知道还有一些额外的内存可以用。
P memory hierarchy, we know we have some additional memory we can use.
一个是寄存器，也就是本地内存，另一个是共享内存。
One is the register, that is local memory, the other is shared memory as well.
好的，那我们会尝试利用它们。
Okay, so we'll try to utilize them.
好的。那么你是怎么利用它们的呢？
Okay. So how do you utilize them.
所以与其让……好的，请说。
So instead of letting, yeah, please.
寄存器的数量，和CPU的寄存器数量类似吗？
Is the amount of registers, similar to how much registers
有点不一样。
CPU? It's slightly different.
在GPU中，通常一个流式多处理器有固定数量的线程。
So in GPU, usually one streaming multiprocessor have a fixed number of threads.
这些线程会共享该块中所有的寄存器。
And those threads are shared by all those registers are shared among all the threads in that block.
嗯嗯，这样说有道理吗？好的。
Yeah, yeah. Does that make sense? Okay.
这意味着如果你为每个线程分配更多的寄存器，你就能拥有更少的线程。
Which means that if you allocate more register per thread, and you are going to have less threads.
如果是这样的话，那么你就需要在那个流多处理器中共享一些寄存器，对吧？
If, so then you need to share some register built into that stream multiprocessor, okay?
哦。
Oh.
不，寄存器绝对要快得多。
No, register is definitely much faster.
是的。好的，明白了，酷。
Yeah. Okay. Okay, cool.
所以我们改进的第一步是尝试更多地利用寄存器。
So our first step to improve this we try to utilize a little bit more on the register.
在之前的程序中，我们每个线程只用了一个寄存器，
So in the previous program, we only use one register per
现在我们准备多用一些。
spread now we are going to use a little bit more.
如果你还记得CPU里的寄存器分配，我们做的是让你在循环里，
And if you recall the telling register telling in CPU, what we do is we let u in a loop,
做一些内存重用，对吧。
we do some memory reuse, right.
我们让每次循环读取的不止一个元素，这样可以做更多的内存操作。
We let each, each loop we read a little bit more than one element, so we can do more memo.
所以这里，高层次的想法是，嗯，不是让
So here, the high level idea is, um instead of let
每个线程只计算结果中的一个元素。
each thread compute just one element in the result.
我们可以让每个线程计算一个 V 乘 V 的子矩阵。
We can let E thread to compute a V by V sub matrix.
而这个 V 显然是我们的决定性因素。
And this V is apparently our telling factor.
这和 CPU 的分块方式非常相似。
It's very similar to the CPU telling.
这个图基本上给你一个高层次的概念。
This figure basically give you a high level idea.
所以不是只计算那一个元素，我要把它扩展成 V 乘
So instead of computing that one element, and I'm going to extend it a bit into V by
V。我会让每个线程从 A 中抓取几行，而不是一行，
V. I'm going to let E thread to grab a few rows instead of one row from A
并且从 B 中抓取几列，而不是一列，
and a few columns inside of one column from
我进行某种子矩阵的乘法，然后把结果写回去。
B. I perform some sort of submetrix multiply and I write the result spec.
那么为什么这样可以减少内存呢？
So why this can reduce memory?
因为如果你从B的角度来看，每次我读取B的时候，
Because if you look at B, from the perspective of B, every time I read the B,
我可以复用之前从A的ad读取的数据，对吧？
I can reuse the previous read from the ad of A, right?
所以这里有一些内存复用。
So there are some memory reuse.
好的，我们来尝试实现这个核函数。
Okay. Let's try to implement this kernel.
好的，请大家花30秒看一下这个核函数。
Okay. Please take a look at this kernel for 30 seconds.
好的。
Okay.
好的，是的，我们来运行这个程序。
Okay. Yeah, let's pass this program.
好的，那么和之前的程序相比，
Okay. So from the previous program,
我认为这里的主要区别是，在之前的程序中，我们是直接索引的，
I think the main difference here, in the previous program, we directly index, the
线程索引A和B中的一个元素。
thread index one element from A and B.
但这里我们尝试索引一个块，明白吗。
But here we are trying to index a block, okay.
另一个区别是我们在寄存器中分配数组。
Another difference is we are allocating array in the register.
这意味着我们使用了平方数量的寄存器，相比之前的方式。
So which means that we are using we square registers, compared to the previous one.
我们还分配了一个随机数组，明白吗？
And we are also allocating random array, okay?
我们要做的基本上是，每一次，
And what do we do is basically, uh, every time,
我要读取这一行，再读取这一列，
I'm going to read this row and read this column,
我要把它们相乘，然后把累加的结果写出来，
I'm going to type them together and write the results accumulated results and
然后再写回到这里。
then write it back to here.
明白吗？我还会多读一点，因为我要把这些都读到寄存器里。
Okay? And I'm going to read a little bit more because I'm going to read all this into the register.
所以当我从这一列扫描到那一列时，
So when I scan through this from this column to this column,
我可以复用我之前在这个区域读取的数据，对吧？
I can reuse my previous read on this area, okay?
这样我们就得到了这个循环，就是，嗯，
So that we ended up with this loop that is, um,
我会先为当前线程建立索引，
I'm going to first index for this current thread,
我会先索引出是哪个块
I'm going to first index which block
我要读取，对吧？
I'm going to read, okay?
这基本上就是索引，
And this is basically the index,
X 空间乘以 V 再加 X。好的。
X space times V plus X. Okay.
我用我的线程索引来索引我需要从 A 读取的区域。
I use my thread index to index the area I need to read from A.
然后我会对这里的这一列做类似的事情，好吗？
And then I'm going to do the similar thing for this column here, okay?
一旦我到达了这一行和这一列，
And once I get to this row and column,
我会在一个类似归约循环的内部，再进行一次操作，做点积运算，
I'm going to perform another inside of, like, a reduction loop where I do a dot product
在这一行和这一列的元素之间做点积，并累加结果，对吧。
between those elements of the row and columns and cumulal results, right.
最终，我会把结果写回到这个线程对应的特定块中。
And eventually, I will write the results back into this particular block for this thread.
好的。那么这里和程序的前一个版本相比，
Okay. So here, compared to the previous version of the program,
呃，这个程序做的工作稍微多了一些，对吧？
uh, this program did a little bit more work, right?
所以它计算了整个BV的结果，而不仅仅是单个元素。
So it computes the results of the entire BV instead of just a single element.
你也可以从高层次上理解，如果矩阵的形状不变，
So you can also get a high level sense that is we are going to if the matrix shape is unchanged,
我们将需要更少的线程，因为和之前相比，
we are going to need less threads because compared to the previous one,
之前我们需要平方数量的线程，而这里明显减少了，减少了一个平方因子的数量。
we need squared threads, but here, definitely, by a factor of divided by a factor of square.
好吗？我们来尝试分析一下内存IO。
Okay? Let's try to analyze the memory IO.
所以每个线程的全局内存速率。
So global memory rate per thread.
那就是V加U的平方，对吧？
So it's V plus U square, right?
那为什么是NV加U的平方呢？
So why is NV plus U square?
因为我们基本上要读取这部分，对吧？
Because we are going to basically read this part, right?
还有，我们也要读取这部分。
And also, we are going to read this part.
这些就是我们所有的读取操作。
That's all our read.
好吗？而且这部分只和外层循环有关，对吧？
Okay? And this part is only tied to this outside loop, right?
但这部分和这两个循环都有关系，对吧？
But this part is tied to these two loops, right?
而且每次我们都在读取一个元素。
And every time we are reading an elements.
好吗？所以这就是为什么这个在这个V上是平方的，好吗？
Okay? So that is why this is square on this V, okay?
明白。那么有多少个线程？
Cool. And how many threads?
所以和之前的版本相比，我们现在是未分割乘以未分割乘以波线程，
So compared to the previous version, we are doing undivided by times undivided by wave threads,
现在我们只需要unsquar除以w的平方个线程。
now we only need unsquar divided by w squared threads.
好吗？所以总的全局内存访问基本上是我们把它们
Okay? So the total global memory access is basically we market
合在一起，然后得到这个元素。
them together and we get this element.
和之前的版本相比，我们做得稍微好一点。
Compared to the previous version we did we have been doing a little bit better.
在之前的版本中，我们基本上是二的三次方。
In the previous version, we basically have two cube.
这里我们是一的三次方，基本上是除以V这个因子，所以我们减少了一点。
Here we have one cube, which is basically divided by the factor of V, so we reduce a little bit.
好的。那么对于内存，比如我们用了多少寄存器。
Okay. And for memory, like how many register we use.
所以这是我们用的内存，对吗？
So this is the memory we use, right?
我们基本上是每个线程用W平方加两个浮点数。
We use basically Wquare plus two float per thread.
好的，这部分我们没问题吧？
Okay. Are we good with this one?
很好。所以我觉得这个的核心思想其实就是
Cool. So, I think the high level idea of this one is going to is basically we like
希望每个线程计算一个区域，而不是一个元素。
each thread to compute a region instead of one element.
但从这个标题来看，你知道，这只是1.5，
But from the title of this, you know, this is just 1.5,
我们其实可以在这个区域的基础上做得更好一点。
and we can do a little bit better than this region.
所以我们还是遵循同样的思路，就是我们还是希望每个线程计算一个区域，
So we all follow the same idea as, um, we still like each thread to compute one region,
在C中计算一个结果区域。
one result region in C.
但我们还能不能再优化一下这个程序，这样我们就不用……
But can we still, improve this program a little bit, so we don't have to,
比如说，把这段内容读很多遍。
like, read this many times.
有人有什么想法吗？
Anyone has an idea here?
所以你发现一种高效的方法是，当我做这种分块时，每次基本上都是读取
So one efficient you find is when I do this kind of tiling, every time I basically read
A 的一行和 dira 的一列，然后基本上做一个点积。
one row from A and one column from dira I basically do a dot product together.
而且对于这里每次读取一行，我们还是会多次读取 B，
And for each read of the row here, we are going to read we are still going to read B multiple times,
这里我们读取 B 的元素方式还是立方级别的，对吧？
here the way we read the elements from B is still cube, right?
那我们能不能做得更好？其实是可以的。
So can we do better here? We can right.
有两种方式可以做矩阵乘法。
So there are two ways of doing multiply multiplication.
你可以做行乘以列的点积，这样你可以直接得到一个元素的结果，
You can do a row by column, um, uh, door product, and you directly get the results on one element,
但你也可以做列乘以行的乘积，对吧？
but you can also do column by row product, right?
首先你需要在这里定位那个小区域。
You pick you first locate that small region from here.
然后你在这里取一列，对吧？
And you grab one column here, right?
你还要在这里取一行，把它们相乘。
And you also grab one row here, add them you multip them together and you
你会得到一个结果矩阵，它的形状是V乘以V。
get you get one result matrix, which is the shape of V by
但是这个V乘以V并不是我们最终需要的结果，对吧？
V. But this V by V is not the eventual results we need, right?
所以为了得到最终结果，我们要从这里扫描，也要从这里扫描。
So in order to get eventual results, what we do is we can scan from here and we scan from here
我们基本上读取这里的一小列，这里的一小行。
and we basically read one small column here, one small row here.
这样我们就得到了一个区域的结果。
We basically get one region of results.
然后我们再读取这里的一列和这里的一小行，就得到了另一个区域的结果。
And then we read one column here and one small row here, and we get another region of them.
这就叫做部分和。
And this is called partial sum.
所以每次我们得到一个部分和，基本上我们需要做的就是把所有的部分和相加
So every time we get a partial sum, and what we need to do is basically we add all the partial sum
最终我们就能得到这个区域的最终结果，对吧？
together and we get the eventual results of this region, right?
在这种模式下，你可以看到，对于A，对于每一行，我们仍然需要读取整个区域。
And in this pattern, you can Oh, for A, for each route, we still read the entire region.
而对于B，我们做得更好，因为我们只需要扫描整个区域一次，而不是多次，
And for B, we are doing better because we only need to scan the entire region once instead of times,
对吧？我们来看一下这个。
right? Let's see this.
好的。这个背后的数学直觉其实是，
Okay. Mathematical mathematical intuition behind this is basically,
为了得到这里的结果矩阵，有两种方法。
in order to get that result matrix here, there are two ways.
一种是按行与列相乘。
One is a row by column.
但我们可以用不同的方法来做。
But we can do it differently.
那就是我们可以把这个区域分解成像这样的小子矩阵。
That is we can basically break this region into sub matrix like this.
比如说，我们把这个X拆分成X一，
For example, we break this X into X one,
X二，还有很多很多列。
X two, many many columns.
然后我们把这个Y拆分成Y一，Y二。
And we break this Y into Y one, Y two.
我们发现这个区域其实可以表示为X，
And we find that this region can actually be expressed as X,
Y一加上x2y2。
Y one plus x2y2.
对，如果我们把它拆成很多很多小区域，我们会发现，为了得到这一部分的结果，
Right. And if we break into many many small regions, we find that in order to get this part results,
我们只需要读取这一次，然后再读取这一次。
we only need to read this time once and read this once.
而在之前的版本里，我们需要读取这一次，然后再读取这个三次，对吧？
And in the previous version, we need to read this once and read this cube times, right?
这就是直觉所在。
So that is the intuition.
我们接下来就要按照这个直觉，尝试修改我们之前的程序，
And we are going to follow in this intuition and we try to modify our previous program,
把内核进展到这个版本，可以吗？
progress kernel into this version, okay?
请稍微看一下这个内核。
Please take a look at this kernel little bit.
好的。
Yeah.
所以你的意思是，我从哪里得到这个？
So you mean, where I get this?
嗯哼，对，你是这样得到的，对吧？
Uh huh. Yeah, you get the by, right?
然后你就从左到右，从上到下扫描我的 asthm 全部。
And then you just scan from left, right from top bottom of my asthm altogether.
你得到的是 by V。这样你把两个 s 相乘就得到一个，对吧？在之前，我是这样读的，对吗？
You get the by V. So that you multiply two s get one Yeah, in the previous, I read this, right?
我读的是这一整行。
I read this, this entire row.
之前我读的是这一整行，对吧？
In the previous I read this entire row, right?
然后我读了这一整列，就得到一个元素。
And I read this entire column, I get one element out.
为了得到第二个元素，
And in order to get this second element,
我需要读取这个，我读了这个，还需要再读这个，对吧？
I need to read I read this and I need to read this one again, right?
对。所以基本上，每次读取这一行时，
Yeah. So basically, for each read of this row,
我都需要读取这一整列。
I need to read all this column one.
这就是为什么是平方的，对吧？
That's why it is square, right?
但在这个里面，我只需要读这个和这个。
But in this one, I just need to read this and this.
对，这样说有道理吗？
Yeah. Does that make sense?
这基本上就能让你直观理解为什么这个内存总是更小。
And that basically give you intuition why this memory are always smaller.
好的，嗯，我觉得这个程序，一旦你理解了这个，
Okay. Yeah, uh, I think this program, once you understand this, uh,
分块、矩阵乘法和部分求和，你就能理解这个程序了。
block wise, matrix multiplication and partial sum, you understand this program.
它的作用是仍然使用那个块索引和块
So what it does is it still use that block index and block
D 还有线程索引来定位这个区域，明白吗？
D and also thread index to locate this region, okay?
一旦定位到区域，它会创建完全相同数量的寄存器。
And once it locates the region, it's going to create the exact same amount of registers.
好的。但不是像之前那样循环遍历A的行和B的列，
Okay. But instead of like I loop I loop over the rows of A and the column of B,
我会遍历A的列和B的行。
I'm going to loop over the columns of A and rows of B.
明白了吗？这就是为什么有外层循环K，对吧？
Okay? That's why there's outer loop K, right?
这个K基本上就是沿着这个方向扫描。
This K basically scan following this direction.
每次我都会抓取一个小区域，就是这里的这个区域和这个区域。
And every time I'm going to grab a small area, right here, is this area and this area.
然后我做点积，明白吗？
And I do dot product. Okay?
最后我把所有结果加到这个区域里。
And then I add all the results together into this region.
然后我把所有的部分和加在一起，得到结果。
And I add all the partial sum together and I get the by.
好的。我们来试着分析一下内存IO。
Okay. And let's try to analyze the memory IO.
所以每个线程的全局内存速率是n的平方，对吧？
So the global memory rate per thread is noise and squared, right?
所以这样要好得多，对吧？
So it's much better, okay?
我们需要的线程数基本上也是一样的，对吧？
And the number of threads we need is basically, uh, same, right?
除以w和nib。
Divided by w and nib.
n的平方除以w的平方。
And squared divided by way square.
总的内存访问量是，我们把这些相乘，然后我们发现对于
The total memory access is, we multiply this together, and we find that for
两个三次项，我们可以把它们除以。
both the cubic term, we can divide them by.
好的？我们需要的寄存器数量其实就是w的平方加二，基本上就是我们分配的这部分。
Okay? And the number register we need is also we square plus two, essentially this part we allocate.
好的，酷。这个我们没问题吧？
Okay. Cool. Are we good with this one?
没问题。
Yeah.
所以你的意思是，可以交换它们。
So you mean, yeah, you can swap them.
没关系，没关系，没关系。无所谓。
It's fine. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Doesn't matter.
就像这样乱七八糟的。
It's just like messes make like this.
好吧？好的，酷。
Yeah. Okay? Okay, cool.
这已经是Mtmo的一个相当不错的版本了。
This is already a pretty good version of Mtmo.
我觉得在很多现在的机器架构中，如果你只有
I think in many today's machinery frameworks, if you only have
一层内存层级，最后就会变成这样。
one layer of memory hierarchy, you end up with this one.
明白吗？但我们还没结束，对吧？
Okay? But we are not ending here, right?
所以我们知道我们有另一层内存层次结构。
So we know we have another layer of memory hierarchy.
也就是说我们想要使用共享内存。
That is we want to use our shared memory.
好的，所以我们最初的内容就在这里，对吧？
Okay. So our initial content was here, right?
我们必须通过这个内存层次结构来读取
And we have to go through this memory iarchy we read
从这里到共享内存，然后到寄存器。
it from here to shared memory then to registers.
明白了吗？现在，我们要让事情变得越来越复杂。
Okay? Now, we are going to make things more and more complicated.
那么，基本上如何利用共享内存，并尝试
So how to basically leverage shared memory and try
在GPU上实现这种两级分块或数学运算。
to implement this two level telling or math on GPS.
所以这里的直觉其实还是很直接的，但编码会有点难度。
So here, the intuition is still quite straightforward, but the coding is a little bit difficult.
好的，呃，在讲座中，
Okay, uh, in the lecture,
我将重点讲解直觉理解。
I'm going to focus on intuition.
我认为如果你是新手，这会非常难，
I think it's very hard to if you are new to this,
很难向你解释得非常清楚。
it's very hard to explain this very clearly to you.
所以请在课程中多花些时间学习这个内容。
So please put time on this on the program.
但我会给你一些直观的理解。
But I'm going to give you intuition.
在这里，如果你还记得CPU中的M，对吧，
So here, if you still remember the uh, met M in CPU right,
还记得那个程序吗，我们做了两级划分。
remember that program, we do two level telling.
其实我们就是不断地划分、划分、再划分，对吧。
The thing is basically we keep telling and telling telling, right.
我们做的是递归划分。
We do a recursive telling.
我们先在某个形状上划分，然后在那个小形状内部我们还会继续
We first tell it at some shape and then inside of that small shape we're going to
告诉人类更小的船只矩阵。
tell human smaller ship matrix.
所以在这里，我们要做的是让大家知道我们正在使用SM，也就是共享内存。
So here, what we do is we try to let know we are using the SM, which is shared memory.
记住，共享内存在块级别上。
Remember shared memory is at the block level.
所以同一个块中的所有线程都可以访问那块共享内存。
So all the threads in one block is going to access to that shared memory.
我们要做的是让每个块去计算一个区域，对吧？
So what we do is we let each block to compute a region, right?
这个区域在这里用L乘L来表示。
And this region is denoted here as L by L.
然后我们知道，在块内部，所有线程都可以访问那块共享内存，
And then we know that inside of the block, all the threads can access that shared memory
所以他们可以一起协作来计算by，对吧？
so they can work together to calculate by, right?
然后对于每个线程，我们会让它们计算一个更小的子区域，
And then for each thread, we are going to let them to compute a smaller sub region
这个子区域来自这个L乘L，本质上就是by。
from this by L, which is essentially by.
好的。白板讲解有帮助，是因为我们用到了内存，对吧？所以请思考一下这一点。
Okay. And white telling can help because of memory we use, right? So think about this.
当我们计算这个小的区域时，我们本质上需要这一行。
So when we compute this small regime by, right, we essentially need this row.
我们需要读取这一行，对吗？
We need to read this row, right?
而且这些有很多行，不只是单独一行，是这一块的多行，好吗？
And these are many roles, not just a single, this block of rows, okay?
我们还需要读取这一部分的列，对吧？
And we need to read this part of column, right?
但是当我们计算这个区域时，我们需要什么？
But when we compute this regime, what do we need?
所以我们仍然需要很多行，对吧？但我们需要读取的是这个。
So we still need the many rules, right? But we need to read this.
这就是提前读取的作用，如果我们提前把一部分数据读入，
This is the hoteling works because if we basically perform some reading ahead of time,
也就是说，我们把这一部分读到共享内存里并保存在那里，好吗？
that is we read this part into the shared memory and keep it there, okay?
然后在线程层面，我们会遍历很多很多列，所以我们
And then at the thread level, we are going to iterate through the many many columns so we
这样我们在读取时基本上可以实现内存复用。
can basically have some memory reuse for this reading.
因此，我们节省了一些内存，对吧？
Therefore, we save some memory, okay?
同样的道理，对吧？你基本上也可以这样做。
And same thing, right? And you can basically do this.
好吗？这就是 tally。接下来我会稍微演示一下这个程序，也许给你们30秒时间。
Okay? This is tally. And I'm going to show this program a little bit, maybe give you 30 seconds.
我觉得这个有点难。
And I think this one is hard.
是的。请大家课后花点时间理解一下这个内容。
Yeah. Please spend some time later after the class to understand this one.
嗯。
Yeah.
好的，我现在给大家讲一些总体思路。
Okay, I'm going to give you some high level things.
好，你可以从不同角度去理解同步。
Okay, so you can think about sync either way.
首先你注意到的区别就是这行代码，对吧？我开始用这个了。
First the difference you noted is this line, right, where I started using
this prefix to allocate memory from SRM.
A? So I allocate two chunks of memory, one is SA, the other SB.
Here, I simplify a little bit because we should allocate one of the shape
of S by L and the other is the shape of L by S.
But I basically unify them a little bit, because you can think that I transpose
the matrix a little bit, okay?
So I'm going to allocate memory for this part and for this part in shared memory.
Okay. And what I'm going to do is I'm going to scan
from here to here and here to here at the block level.
Okay? And I like each block to basically scan from here to here, here to here and compute this part.
在这个代码块内部，
And inside of this block, what
我要做的是让每个线程读取这部分和这部分的一小块区域。
I'm going to do is I will like each thread to read a little region
对，每个线程会读取这块和那块的一小块区域。
of this and a little region of this.
好的，我还有一个内部循环，让我把这里稍微整理一下。
Right. I have another inner loop that basically let me clean this a little bit.
我有另一个内部循环，它其实就是读取这部分的小区域，然后我从这里扫描到这里。
I have another inner loop which basically reads a small area of this and I scan from here to here.
抱歉，是从这里到这里，还有从这里到这里。
Sorry, from here to here and here to here.
这是递归的，一个是在块级别上说明，另一个是在线程级别上说明。
This is recursive, one is basically telling at the block level and the other is basically telling
好，我首先会用我的块索引来索引这个区域，对吧？
at uh the thread level.
这就是我正在做的，我在索引这个区域。
Okay. I'm going to first use my block index to index this region, right?
And this is what I'm doing. I'm indexing it regi.
我基本上是从HBM开始读取数据，因为A和B都分配在HBM上。
I basically start reading things from HBM because it's A and B, allocated on HBM, I
我把数据从GBM读取到我的共享内存中。
reading things from GBM to my shared memory.
明白吗？而且这行代码是有问题的，因为如果你还记得窗口求和的话，
Okay? And the and this line of code is problematic because if you still remember the window sum,
在窗口求和的例子中，当我让所有线程从GPM读取数据到共享内存时，
in the Window sum example, when I try to let all threads to read things from GPM to share memory,
我需要做的是对读取操作进行分区，
what I do is I need to also partition read,
我只让每个线程读取其中的一部分。
I only let each thread to read one part of it.
这被称为协作式获取。
And this is called cooperative fetching.
我觉得我们之前稍微讲过一点。还记得吗？
I think we covered a little bit. Still remember?
好的，这里我把代码稍微简化了一下，因为我们之后会
Okay. And here I simplify this code a little bit because we are going to
讲解如何实现这个数据块。
cover how we implement this chunk later.
但总体思路是你不能让所有线程都去读取所有区域到共享内存中。
But the high level idea is you cannot just let all threads to read all the regions
因为这个共享内存将会被块中的所有线程访问。
into shared memory because this shared memory is going to be
所以每个线程只负责读取自己那一部分。
accessed by all the threads in the block.
是的，我希望在我读了一点之后能写一些代码部分。
So each thread only is responsible for reading its own part.
好的。如果你还记得那两个同步线程，为什么我们这里需要同步线程？
Yeah, I hope to write some code part in I read a little bit.
是的，这是共享内存。
Okay. And if you still remember the two sync threads, why we need a syn thread here?
我需要等这个任务完成后，才能开始访问那部分内存，对吧？
Yeah, it's shared memory.
否则就会出现不确定的区域和不确定的行为。
I need to wait for this to finish the job, and then I can start access that part of memory, right?
为什么我需要这个同步操作？
Otherwise, there will be undetermined area, undetermined behavior.
为什么我需要这个同步线程？
Why I need this single stress?
因为我想避免某个线程在这里正确完成计算后
Because I want to avoid that one thread properly finish the computation here and
回到那个循环的下一次迭代，
come back to the next iteration of that loop,
我想避免那个线程开始读取数据。
I want to avoid that thread to start reading.
我想确保所有线程都完成计算并且基本上已经累加了结果，
I want to make sure all threads finish the computation and basically accumulated results,
然后我加一个屏障，再开始读取新的内容。
and then I add a barrier and I start reading new contents.
这就是这里的下一列。
That is the next columns here.
所以这就是为什么我需要在这里再加一个屏障，好吗？
So that's why I need to add another barrier here, okay?
所以有了这个屏障，你可以理解这个循环基本上是在读取
So with this barrier, you understand that this loop is doing is basically reading
这个区域，读取这个区域。
this area, reading this area.
好吗？然后我们要做的基本上就是这个。
Okay? And then what we do is basically this is something that
这就是我们在上一页幻灯片中讨论的内容，对吧。
we have been talking about in the last slide, right.
我们基本上是用ress级别的分配来处理这个乘法。
We basically use ress level telling to handle the multiplication of this.
好吗？我们让每个线程从中取一个更小的区域，然后我们还有另外三层循环，
Okay? We each thread to take a smaller region from that and we have another three layer loop,
你可以看到，这就像我们在不断累加结果，
and you can see, this is like we are accumulating results from all the way
从这里到这里，以及这个内部。
from here to here and inside of this.
所以我们把所有的结果都加到最终的结果条目里，好吗？
So we are adding all the results together into the result entry, okay?
是的。关于这个程序里的控制和这里的情况，
Yeah. Like to report about the control and the here in this program,
我觉得这里没有控制流，对吧？
I don't think there's a control flow, right?
这种情况非常少见。非常少见，但以防万一，因为有时候可能某个核心
It's very unlikely. It's very unlikely, but just in case, because sometimes maybe one core get
比其他核心的功率稍微高一点。
a little bit higher power than the other.
是的，因为物理原因。
Yeah, because of physics.
是的，确实如此。
Yeah, it really is.
但我这样做是为了代码的安全。
But I spell this is for the safety of the code.
因为你不知道这种情况会不会发生，这很难争论。是的。
Because you don't know if this happens, it's very hard to debate. Yeah.
好的，好的，花点时间吧。
Okay. Okay, spend some time.
基本上，我们和之前的版本相比，在这个区域做了什么？
Basically, what do we do compared to the previous versions, basically at this area?
是的，这个区域的代码基本上是在块级别上说明的。
Yeah, this regional code that basically telling at the block level.
同样地，我们可以对内存IO进行计算，我会把结果展示给你。
Similarly, we do we can do calculation on memory IO, and I'm going to present results to you.
这个我就留给你自己处理了。
I'm going to leave this to yourself.
但我觉得这部分比理解代码要简单，因为你要做的是，
But I think this part is easier than understanding the code because what you do is,
呃，你基本上就是读循环，然后统计分配了多少寄存器和共享内存，
uh, you basically read the loop, and you count how many registers and shared memory allocated and
还有在内存层级之间发生了多少IO操作。
how many IO is happening between memory hierarchies.
好的，看这部分，对吧？
Okay. Looking at this part, right?
我说这段代码有问题，因为如果我这样读我的代码，
I said this part of code is problematic because if I read my code in this way,
那就意味着我所有的线程都会去读取
that means that all my thress is going to read
整个区域到共享内存里，这样是不对的。
the entire region into the shared memory, which is wrong.
首先，这样很慢。我也不知道该怎么做，对吧？
First, it is it is slow. I don't how to do that, right?
其次，会有一些冲突，比如说，
Second, um, there will be some conflicts, for example,
有些线程把数据读到那个寄存器，哦不，是那个共享内存条目里，
some threads reading things into that register, sorry, that shared memory entry,
另一个线程也在做同样的事情，他们就会发生冲突。
another thread is doing the same thing and they are going to have some conflict.
所以我们需要做的是更改这个协议，这其实是一种非常非常常见的方法
So what do we do is we need to change this protocol, and this is a very very common approach
在GPU中被称为协作抓取。
in GPU called cooperative fetching.
也就是所有线程从一个源区域抓取内存，比如说从GPM到目标区域。
That is all fetching memory from one source area, for example, GPM into a destination area.
而这种协作抓取也需要以SMD的方式来实现。
And this cooperative fetching also need to be implemented in a way that is SMD.
所以我们需要，开发者有责任去思考哪个区域，
So we need to it's the developer's responsibility to think about which region,
哪个分区应该负责，并尝试计算
which is separating that should be responsible for and try to calculate
一点点偏移量，让我们能写入新内容并把数据写入SM，
the offset a little bit and let us write to fresh things and write things into SM,
就是写入，写入，呃，共享内存。
into into into the uh, shared memory.
所以这行代码的真正实现应该是这样的。
And so the true implementation of this line should be looking like this.
我会让你们看这段代码15秒，因为我觉得这个很简单，好吗？
And I will let you guys look at this for 15 seconds because I think this one is easy, okay?
好的。
Okay.
嗯，如果你熟悉C++编程和索引的话，
Um, so if you are familiar with C plus pass programming and indexing,
你应该知道你在做什么，对吧？
you know what you've been doing, right?
基本上，对于这一组线程，
So basically, for this block of threads,
我会获取一个线程ID，然后用线程ID来计算
I'm going to get a thread ID, and then I use thread ID to calculate
当前线程负责哪个条目。
which entry are responsible for this current thread.
对于当前这个线程，
And for this current thread,
我只会索引我负责读取的那个元素，
I'm going to only I'm going to index that element I'm responsible for reading and
并把它读到共享内存里，对吧？
read it into shared memory, right?
是的，非常标准的偏移索引代码，用C++写的，挺酷的。
Yeah, very standardized offsetting indexing code, in CPlusPas Okay, cool.
基本上，在我看来，这是本课程中第二难的代码。
That basically is, in my opinion, the second most difficult code in this class.
好的。我们稍后会和Flash教学联系一下，
Okay. And we are going to touch base with flash teaching later,
那个会比这个更复杂。
and that one will be more complicated than this one.
但这是第二难的。
But this is the second difficult.
所以只要你能很好地理解这段代码，
So as long as you get a good understanding of this code,
我认为你已经完成了Flash教学的一半。明白了吗？
I think you already finished half of flashing teaching. Okay?
明白了吗？很好。那我们把这一部分收尾吧，因为我们最近两节课
A good? Cool. Okay, let's wrap up this part, okay, because we have been doing a lot of
都在做很多GPU编程。
GPU programming in the recent two lectures.
嗯，其实还有很多GPU架构我没有讲到，
Um, so there are many more GP organization I didn't cover,
但我这周给你们布置了一些阅读材料，对吧？
but I give you some readings, in this week, right?
有一些关于如何理解GPU性能的资料。
There are some readings on how to understand the GPU performance.
我认为在我们的文档中，媒体部分提供了很多相关的资料，
And I think in our documentation, media provides a lot of readings,
有一天如果你需要用到这些，你就知道去哪里找相关的指引了，好吗？
and someday if you need to use that, you know where to find pointers, okay?
但总体来说，还有其他几个重要的方面可以让TPO内核运行得更快。
But in general, um, there are a few other important aspects to make TPO kernel fast.
第一个就是全局内存的连续读取。
The first one is global memory continuous read.
也就是说，当我需要读取时，
That is when I myths write to read
AHGPM我需要确保它们是连续读取的。
AHGPM I need to make sure that they read continuously.
我不能只读取一个元素，然后加一个偏移再去读取另一个元素，因为我们知道
I cannot read one element and apply offset and it's going to read another element because we know
即使是在CP内存中，这样做也是很慢的，因为我们要避免带偏移的读取。
that even in CP memory, this is slow because we want to avoid reading with offsets.
我们总是要进行连续读取。
We want to always do continuous read.
好的，嗯，共享内存银行冲突。
Okay uh, shared memory bank conflict.
我觉得这里我只是给你一个更高级的名字，好吗？
I think here I'm just giving you a fancier name, okay?
但是这些事情
But the things that
我觉得这个术语你已经理解了，记得在这个协作式抓取中，
I think this term you already understands, remember in this cooperative fetching,
如果我让所有线程去读取
if I let all threats to read
GBM而不计算这个偏移量，就会有一些冲突，我们称之为银行冲突。
GBM without calculating this offset, there will be some conflict, and we call this bank conflict.
好的。有时候我们需要避免这种共享内存银行冲突，对吧？
Okay. And sometimes we need to avoid this kind of shared memory bank conflict, okay?
还有流水线规划，这个很容易理解，对吧？
Also pipe planning, and this one is very easy to understand, right?
因为我们有内存层级结构，有不同的线程在做IO和计算。
So because we have memory hierarchies, we have different stress doing IO and doing competition.
所以为了节省时间，我们可以让一些线程去做读取和
So in order to even save time, we can add some stress to doing reading and
另一组线程正在进行竞争。
another group of thread doing competition.
然后我们可以重叠内存IO和计算时间。
And then we can overlap the memory IO and computing time.
我们不知道如何按顺序完成这件事。
We don't know how to do it in sequential order.
还有另外两件事，一个是张量核心，
Another two things, one is tensor core,
我希望你们已经读过我给你们的阅读材料，我认为你们已经理解了
I hope you guys already read the readings I give to you, and I think you understand
张量核心的作用，对吧？
what is tensor core doing, right?
它是一个为MTM更专业化的核心，好吗？
It's a more specialized core for MTM, okay?
所以它在MTM中会更快。
So it will be faster in MT
最后一个是低精度，我们下周会讲这个内容。
M. And the last one is lower precision, which we'll cover next week.
好的，酷。这基本上涵盖了GPU讲座的所有内容。
Okay. Cool. That basically covers all the lecture contents for GPUs.
有什么问题吗？好的。
Any question? Okay.
那我们继续。如果我们回头再看这个程序，我们会发现，是的，
Then let's move forward. So if we come back to revisit this program, we find that, yeah,
我们有一个大致的思路，知道如何实现这个内核，如何利用这些内存层次结构。
we have a high level idea how to do this uh kernel how to basically utilize those memory hierarchy.
但如果我让你来做，你还是会遇到很多问题。
But if I ask you to do this, you are still going to face a lot of problem.
因为请记住，在CPU调优中，有几个关键的调优因素。
Because remember in CPU tolling, there are a few tolling factors that are critical.
比如说，你使用共享内存的方式不能超过
For example, the way you use shared memory cannot exceed the limit the
设备所提供的共享内存的限制。
shared memory provided by the device.
这里也是一样，你应该申请多少个线程？
Same thing here, how many threads should you ask for?
好的。你到底应该使用多少寄存器？
Okay. How many regiers you should exactly use?
显然，这不能超过该流处理器中的寄存器数量，对吧？
Apparently, it cannot exceed the number of regiers in that streaming microprocessor, okay?
那我应该为我的程序申请多少SRAM呢？
And how many amount of SRAM should I ask for for my program?
因为不同的设备有不同数量的SRAM，对吧？
Because different devices have different number SRAM, okay?
这基本上就是你实现这个内核时需要考虑的实际问题。
And this is basically the practical concerns when you implement this kernel.
即使你能写出整个程序的代码，也不能保证这个程序
And even if you can write the entire code of this program, it's not guaranteed that this program
是高效的，因为你还需要为这个内核调整超参数配置。
is efficient because you still need to tune the hyperparameters configurations for this kernel.
在机器学习中，我们称之为内核调优，而且有很多框架
And imagine learning, we call this kernel tuning, and there are a lot of frameworks
比如petard和tender flow。
like petard and tender flow.
当你把它们部署到你的模型上时，你会花很长时间
When you just set it up on your model, you are with a pretty long time for
来分析程序并尝试调整这些参数。
it to profile program and try to tune those parameters.
这基本上就是内核调优。
That's basically kernel tuning.
而Kert调优是一个非常困难的问题，因为我们有太多模型了，
And Kert tuning is a very difficult problem because, uh we have so many models,
transformer、STRs Net，它们有不同的算子。
transformers, STRs Net, they have different operators.
每个算子本身都有不同的形状。
Each operator ready have different shape.
比如说，metam的1k×1k和4k的配置肯定和我在这里用的配置不一样，
For example, metam of one kb one k and fourk definitely different than the configurations
因为它们需要不同的处理能力，
that I applied on this telling because they require different amount of processing power
还有内存层级的容量也不同。
and also the memory hierarchy capacity.
当然，还有不同的框架，这个我们已经讲过了。
There are different frameworks, of course, we already covered that.
我认为让事情变得最复杂的，是有很多不同的设备，不同的GPU。
I think the thing that makes since most complex is there are many different devices, different GPUs.
比如说，media本身就有很多代不同配置的GPU，对吧？
For example, media itself has so many generations of GPUs with different configurations, right?
还有CPU。
And there are also CPUs.
有CDN，还有像TPU这样的加速器，我们也想在iPhone和MacBook上部署我们的内核。
There are CDN, uh, there are like TPU bacons, we also want to deploy our kernels
对吧？
on iPhone MacBook, right?
所以这让事情变得复杂了。
So which makes this things complicated.
如果你让开发者来做这件事，比如说，即使只是针对一个Mdm，你也得，
Uh, so if you ask developers to do this, for example, even for a single Mdm, you have to, like,
至少每家公司，比如苹果，
at least every company, Apple,
英特尔，他们都需要雇一堆工程师来调优内核，对吧。
Vd Intel, they need to hire a bunch of engineers to tune the kernels, right.
他们基本上是在处理同样的原始代码，
They are basically working on the same original code,
但他们只需要调整不同的内核参数。
but they just need to tune different kernel parameters.
好吧，实际上有两种解决方案。
Okay? There are essentially two solution to this.
一种就是你雇更多的人，就像我刚才提到的，你让专家来定制。
One is you just hire more people, and like I already mentioned, you ask the experts to craft
你每天都在优化这些内核的性能，并且给他们发工资。
those kernels and tune their performance day by day and you give them salary.
你列举出所有这些冲突，并确保在分析后，一切都没问题。
You enumerate all these conflicts and make sure, yeah, it is good after profile.
第二种解决方案基本上是一个更有野心的方案，
The second solution is basically a more ambitious solution that is
这基本上就是机器工程编译器人员正在做的事情。
basically what machinering compiler people are doing.
他们的想法是，我给你一个系统，也就是一个编译器，
They are saying, like, how about I give you a system, which is a compiler,
你把你的算子给我，同时也把你的设备给我，
and you give me your operator, and you also give me your devices,
然后你把它们都交给那个编译器，那个编译器会
and you through them to that compiler, and that compiler will
自动为你搞定一切。
automatically figure out everything for you.
好的，这基本上就把我们带到了第二部分，
Okay. That basically brings us into the second part of,
还有一个非常重要的话题——应急系统。
uh, and also a very important topic emergency system.
我认为，在2018年到2020年之间，整个社区，
I think, between the year 2018 and 2020, uh, the entire community,
他们都在做编译器，因为他们真的很喜欢这个愿景
they are doing compilers because they are really like this vision
因为这样可以减少人力，对吧？
because they can reduce labors, right?
他们可以给工程师发工资。
They can pay salary to engineers.
他们尝试实现一些自动化。
They try to automate something.
好的，这里是机器编译。
Okay. So here is machining compilation.
显然，机器编译的主要目标是
Obviously the primary goal of machining compilation is
我尝试在内核代码上自动生成最优配置，
I try to automatically generate optimal configurations on the kernel code,
给用户提供高级代码，比如用ten flow Petro甚至Python编写的代码，
giving users high level code, for example, written in ten flow Petro or even Python,
以及目标硬件，如果我能建立这一层，
and target hardware, if I can build this layer,
那么这将会成为超级力量，因为它能够
then this is going to be superpower because it's going to
把任何代码转换成高效版本，基本上消除人工劳动，对吧？
compare any code into a highly efficient version and basically eliminate human labor, okay?
那我们来看看机器编译器和传统编译器有何不同。
So let's look at how machining compiler is different from traditional compiler.
好吗？我希望你们都至少知道什么是传统编译器，对吧？
Okay? So I hope you guys all took at least, know what is traditional compiler, right?
基本上，比如说你写一些代码，
It's basically, for example, when you write some code,
C++，你可以用任何方式来写。
C plus plus, you can write in whatever way.
但是编译器会保证解析你的代码并让它变得非常高效，对吧。
But compiler will guarantee that they pass your code and make it very efficient, right.
它还会把你的代码转化为一些机器指令，
It also lower your code into some machine instructions
这样处理器才能理解，对吧？
and so the instruct the processors can understand, right?
这就是传统编译器。
So this is a traditional compiler.
人类基本上会写一些代码，比如说C++或者其他语言。
Human basically write some code, for example, CPP or whatever.
然后编译器会接收你的代码。
And the compiler will take your code.
它会去除所有那些低效的代码、重复的代码、不必要的代码。
It will eliminate all those efficient code or repeated code, unnecessary code.
接着它会尝试把代码转换成另一种格式，
And then it will try to lower it into another format that is probably not
这种格式可能人类看不懂，但计算机可以识别。
human readable, but the process readable.
指令。好的，我需要把指令给到，呃，基本上是给到
Instructions. Okay. I need to give the instruction to, uh, uh, basically to
目标硬件，然后硬件会根据你的代码来运行。
the target hardware and hardware will ask you your code.
想象一下学习，这其实很相似。
E. Imagine learning, this is very similar.
这里我基本上画了一个堆栈结构。
And here I basically draw the stack here.
记住，沉浸式学习就像我们写代码一样。
Remember immerse learning how we write code.
我们基本上是在组合数据流图，我们使用Tinder flow和Patrig API，
We basically compose dataflow graphs, we use Tinder flow and Patrig API,
并且我们试图处理这一层。
and we try to take care of this layer.
我们把关于模型的想法转化为数据流图，对吧？
We convert our idea about our model into dataflow graph, okay?
编译器的承诺基本上就是，从这里开始，
And the promise of compiler is basically, starting from there,
你不需要去优化比如图变换，也不需要去优化你的内核代码，
you don't have to optimize say graph transformation, you don't have to optimize your kernel code
或者其他的，像是随机调度之类的。
or whatever, random scheduling.
我会为你提供一个全栈解决方案。
And I'm going to take a full stack solution for you.
我会接管。我会接管你的代码。
I'm going to take over. I will take your code.
我会自动把它转化为数据流图。
I will automatically transform it into Dataflograph.
然后我有一些代码会自动进行转换。
And then I have some code that will automatically translate
将你的数据流图转化为高效的版本。
your data flow graph into efficient version.
一旦我得到了最终版本的数据流图，我基本上会这样做：我会问你
And then once I have the eventual version of data flograph what I do is basically I ask you
按照算子定义，从前向和后向进行推导。
from forward and backward following the operator definition.
我还会帮助你为
So I will also help you to generate efficient kernel code for
你在数据流图中使用的每个算子生成高效的内核代码。
each operator you use in your data flograph.
好的，这就是机器编译器试图实现的目标。
Okay. And this is what machining compiler tries to permiss.
一旦你加上这一层，
And once you add this layer,
我觉得我们就可以了，因为只要我们有了高效的内核代码，
I think we are good because once we have that efficient kernel code,
正如我们在前几节课中学习的那样，我们可以直接把代码交给Quota
we studied in the previous several lectures, we can just give the code to Quota
编译器或者其他任何编译器。
compiler or whatever compiler.
And they will basically they will basically take over and transform it into machine code.
You can see machining compiler is slightly higher level than traditional compiler.
It will take your data flow graph and compile it all the way down into kernel code and
then traditional compiler will take over.
Okay. Any problem here?
Okay, this is a pretty big scope because if you have a compiler, that means most of the marchey
system problem will be solved.
Okay. So so what kind of problem we face here?
So uh, apparently, there are three layers.
At the first layer, programming level, we face very difficult program
这会自动将开发者编写的任意且通常是命令式的代码，
that is automatically transform arbitrary and usually imperative code by developers,
转换为兼容的代码。
into a compatible code.
我记得我们在第二节课上讨论过这个问题。
And I think we talked about this in the second lecture.
这已经相当困难了，因为就像我说的，数据流图是非常静态的，
This is already pretty hard because like I said, dataflow graph is so static,
但用户代码却非常动态。
but user code are so dynamic.
这里存在一个差距，我们要怎么做。
And there's a gap, how we do that.
我们之前有提到过这个问题，希望你们还记得。
We touch based on that. I hope you still remember.
你可以看到，这个研究领域基本上是由
And you can see this area of research is basically being
大多数编程语言领域的人在进行的。
conducted by most of programming language people.
编程语言领域的人非常喜欢做这件事，他们都关注这个领域，也就是把
Programming language people really like doing this and they all look at this area that is taking
你的机器学习代码，尝试把你的动态代码转换成静态代码。
your machine learning code and try to convert your dynamic code into study code.
好吗？这和编程语言有关系，对吧？
Okay? And this touch base with programming language, okay?
在图的层面上，编译器的基本工作是，
In a graph level, what the compiler does is basically,
我们尝试执行一些自动的图变换。
we try to perform some automatic graph transformation.
我们在之前的课程中也稍微谈到过这个。
We also talked about this a little bit, in our early lectures.
也就是说，我们有一个静态网络，可以在多次运行中进行优化，最终得到一个
That is, we have a stNt we can optimize it in many runs and then eventually get a graph
比如快30倍的图之类的。
that is 30 times faster or something.
这基本上是由一些图论领域的人来做的。
And this is basically being touchb by some graph theory people.
他们喜欢在图中做分析，所以他们拿到图后会尝试找到等价的图。
Okay, they like to analyze in graphs, so they take graphs and try to find the equivalent graphs.
好的。那么在最后一层，我们主要做的就是这个，对吧？
Okay. And at the last layer, what do we do is helping heavily doing this, right?
那么，如何让算子变得更快呢？
So how to make operator fast.
基本上，他们会采用你算子的高级定义，比如说metamor。
So basically, they will take a high level definition of your operator, for example, metamor.
当你在Python里写Metamo时，实际上你做的是一个层循环。
When you write Metamo in Python, what you do is basically you do a layer loop.
但他们会把这个循环拿去，尝试生成非常高效的内核代码。
But they will take that loop and they try to generate a very efficient kernel code
这正是我们在本讲第一部分做的事情。
that we did in the first part of this tecture.
也就是自动生成那种代码。
Which is auto those kind of code.
好的，比如在GPU上的coda，这会自动化整个过程。
Okay, coda, on GPS and which was automate the entire process. Okay.
嗯，这是一个相当大的领域，但在本讲中，因为你还记得整体框架，
Um, uh, this is a pretty big area, but in this lecture because you still remember the big picture,
我们正在尝试优化算子代码。
we are trying to optimize operator code.
所以我会简单介绍一下如何用编译器来做这件事。
So I'm going to touch base a little bit on how to do this using compilers.
好的。在接下来的课程中，我们会涉及到其他层级，对吧？
Okay. And in later lectures, we are going to touch base other layers, okay?
所以在那之前，我想给大家一个关于编译器领域整体情况的高层次介绍。
So before that, I want to give you a high level picture what is going on in the compiler domain.
我会列举几个著名的编译器，并向大家介绍它们的主要内容。
So I'm going to lame a few famous compilers and give you an introduction of what they are cooking.
以及这些编译器背后的人物，对吧？
And what are the people behind them, okay?
第一个当然是来自谷歌的，叫做XLA，
So the first one, of course, from Google, right, uh, it's called XLA,
如果你看XLA的Logo，
XLA, if you look at Logo.
它和TensorFlow的标志非常相似，对吧？
It's very similar to tens TF. Okay?
所以这个XLA实际上，我认为它是第一个面向机器学习的编译器。
So this SLE was actually uh I would say it's the first compiler for machine learning.
它是在2016年和TensorFlow一起发布的。
It was released together with, um, with Tenerflow in 2016.
你可以看到谷歌在这方面有多有前瞻性。
And you can see how Google is, uh, visionary on this.
所以基本上，当他们构建Tener flow的第一个区域时，你就已经在考虑编译器了。
So basically, when they build the first region of tener flow, you already think about the compiler.
是的，因为我认为当他们构建Tener flow时，他们意识到必须让
Yeah, because I think when they build Tener flow, they realize that they have to ask
他们的Google开发者在至少三种硬件上开发超过200个算子，
their Google developers to develop more than 200 operators on at least three kinds of hardware,
包括CPU、GPU和TPU。
CPU GPU and TPU.
这已经有60种组合了，对吧？
And that is already 60 combinations, right?
这会花费大量的时间。
And that takes a lot of time.
所以他们开始思考如何构建一个编译器，这个编译器叫做SOE，如果你看看，
So they start thinking about how to build a compiler, this compiler is called SOE and if you look,
如果你回头看，你会发现，呃，这个编译器非常好，以至于现在，
if you look back, you can see, uh, this is so good that today,
大多数tenser flow的后端都是基于这个的。
most of tenser flows back is based on this one.
所以我的意思是，他们基本上把自己开发者写的所有算子都抛弃了。
So basically what I mean is the throw away all the operators written by their own developers
并且使用SLA来生成代码，可以吗？
and use SLA to generate code. Okay?
SLA也在扩展其范围，以支持petarg和其他任何框架，可以吗？
And SLAs also extending its scope to support petarg and any other frameworks, okay?
第二个编译器是TBM，对吧，Tensor虚拟机。
Second compiler TBM, right, Tensor virtual machine.
这是一个非常非常著名的学术项目。
This is a very, very famous project from academia.
两周后，这个项目的负责人，
And after two weeks, the leader of this project,
TQ Chen，他是CMU的教授。
TQ Chen, was he's a professor at CMU.
他将会为我们做一次嘉宾演讲。
He's going to give us guest talk.
好吗？而且这是学术界最成功的编译器之一，好吗？
Okay? And this one is one of the most successful compiler in academia, okay?
它主要关注的也是开源的，并且主要关注于，
And it mostly focus on it's also open source, and it mostly focus on,
比如说，为推理编译代码，而不是用于训练。
like, compiling code for inference, not for training.
好的。那就意味着TVM生成的代码没有反向传播，对吗？
Okay. That means there's no backward pass for the code generated by TVM, okay?
我认为开发TM的研究人员和学生，他们后来出来创业了，
And I think the researchers and students who develop TM, they went out and do a startup,
创办了一家公司叫octo，融资了不少钱。
which is octo, they raise quite a lot.
我记得大概有两亿美元左右。
I think there is almost 200 M. Okay.
但这家公司经营得不是很好，后来被
But the company was not doing pretty well and it was acquired by
去年以差不多的价格被Amedia收购了。
Amedia last year at a similar price to what the risk.
是的，这是一个令人唏嘘的故事。
Yeah, that is a set story.
好的，明白。第三个你可能知道，这个
Okay. Yeah. Okay. The third one, you probably know, and this is the one
吸引了最多用户，对吧？
that attracts the most user, right?
2.0，呃，本质上就是torch.compile。
2.0, uh, which is essentially torch dot compile.
就像我说的，torch真的很擅长在很晚的时候做某些事情，
And like I said, torch is really good at doing something really late,
但仍然能赢过之前的那些玩家。
but still win over the previous, players.
是的。所以我认为它能赢的原因是，就像我说的，torch一开始是从命令式编程起步的，
Yeah. So I think the reason it wins is because like I said, tort starts from imperative
而且没有编译过程，对吧？
programming without compilation, right?
但他们逐渐过渡到了一个对编译器友好的框架。
But they gradually migrate into a compiler friendly framework.
一旦你拥有了大量已经习惯你编程模型的用户，
Uh once you have a deep user base that is get addicted to your programming model,
他们就不会再切换了，你想加什么功能都可以，他们都会用。
they are not going to switch, and you can add whatever feature you want, and they will use that.
好的，实际上，
Okay. Uh in fact,
Excel比Toti Compil要好得多。
Excel is much better than Toti Compil.
但我觉得人们并不喜欢那样。
But I don't think people like that because
Tn flow 本身太难编程了，好吗？
Tn flow itself is too hard to program, okay?
然后，在某种程度上，他们所做的就是添加一些和编译器相关的接口，
And, and in to two point, all what they do is they add, uh, a few like compiler related,
他们试图倡导大家使用 T D comple。对吧。
interfaces and they are trying to advocate to use T D comple. Yeah.
不，今天 SLE 也可以用于 Torch。
No. Today, SLE also works for Torch.
是的，所以我觉得 Meta 和 Google 他们在合作。
Yeah. So I think Meta and Google they are collaborating.
是的，Torch 想要支持 XOI 的原因是 XLA 是在 TPU 上运行的最佳后端。
Yeah. The reason Torch wants to support XOI is because XLA is the best backend for running on TPUs.
而且像用户或者 petri 这样的人也想把他们的任务部署到 TPU 上，
And people like users or petri they also want to deploy their job on TPUs,
所以他们必须集成，对吧？
so they have to integrate, okay?
这些编译器都是专用的吗？
Each of these compilers are specific?
它们不是特定的框架。
They are not specific frameworks.
我认为现在来看，如果你关注机制，框架的概念其实是很契合的。
I think today, if you look at mechanism, the frameworks concept is kind of fitted.
它更像是一种前端编程语言，一个Bon引擎。
It's more like a front end programming language, a Bon engine.
我基本上可以把我最喜欢的命令式编程语言或者
I can essentially combine my Petros favorite imperative programming language or
编程接口结合到一个基于XOI的bacon中。
programming interfaces to a bacon that is XOI based.
这样也没问题。是的。当然，
That's also fine. Yeah. But of course,
我觉得如果你想要最好的用户体验，你应该用那个框架。嗯，好的。
I think if you want the best user experience, you should use that framework. Yeah. Okay.
关于这个呢，呃，
And for this one, uh,
我觉得你们用得很多。
I think you guys use a lot.
最后一个是modular，好吗？
And the last one is modular, okay?
这个modular是一家公司，今天几乎融资了三亿。
This modular is a company which raised almost 300 today.
好吗？它是由一个叫克里斯·劳特纳的人建造的。
Okay? It was built by a guy called Chris Lautner.
如果你们是编译器方面的人，可能会知道他的名字。
And if you guys are compiler people, you probably know his name.
他是LLVM的发明者之一。
He was an inventor of LLVM.
现在，LLVM是将许多C++代码编译到不同平台的默认编译器。
Okay, LLVM is a default compiler today for compiling many C plus pass code into diverse platforms.
他是最成功的编译器开发者之一。
Okay. He's one of the most successful compiler.
而且这个人显然也想做机器学习相关的事情，
And this guy, apparently, he wants to do machinery as well,
他尝试在一家初创公司里打造世界上最强大的编译器。
and he tried to build under startup that tried to build the world's greatest compilers.
这个人，克里斯·劳特纳，如果你在谷歌上搜索，会找到他。
And this guy, Chris Lateran, if you search Google, you'll find him.
他是非常有名的人，所以他曾经在
He's a very famous people. So he worked for
谷歌工作了几年。
Google for a few years.
嗯，不过，谷歌给了他一个很高的职位，至少是总监级别，
Uh, but, and Google gives him a pretty high title, at least director level,
当然，还有很丰厚的薪资待遇。
and, of course, big package.
但他只在那里工作了一年，而且没能和谷歌的人合作好，
But he only worked there for one year, and he was not able to work with Google people
因为他想推广自己关于编译器的想法，但谷歌并不接受这个。
because he wants to push his own idea on compiler, but Google is not going to accept that.
谷歌想要推动XOI。
Google wants to push XOI.
所以，他基本上就离开了谷歌，加入了苹果公司，好吗？
So, then he basically left Google and joined Apple, okay?
在苹果，他想推广一种叫做Swift的语言。
And in Apple, he wants to push a language called Swift.
所以你们知道，很多很多苹果的应用其实都是用Swift编写的，而不是Python。
So you guys know many many Apple apps are basically program using Swift, not Python.
你可以把Swift理解为一种非常神奇的语言，
And you can understand Swift as a very magical language that
它可以在Python和C++之间进行解释。
can interpret between Python and C plus plus.
所以你可以编写代码，就像今天的机器框架一样。
So you can write, it's like today's machinery framework.
你可以用非常类似于Python的方式来编写，
You can write in a way that is very similar to Python,
非常容易理解，但你可以直接把
very easy to understand, but you can directly convert
那段代码转换成可以编译的符号版本。
that code into a symbolic version that can compile.
所以他真的很喜欢这个，他在谷歌和苹果都大力推动了Swift。
So he really likes that, and he pushed pretty hard on Swift on both Google and Apple.
我觉得他在苹果很成功，很多很多苹果的代码都是用Swift写的。
I think he was successful on Apple and many, many Apples code was written in Swift.
然后在某个时候，他离开了
And then at some point, he left
苹果，开始做这个Modular。
Apple and started doing this modular.
我记得大概一两年前，他创办了这家公司，还发了个帖子说，
And I think while or two years ago, he start this company, posted something like,
他们比之前快了20倍，对吧？
um they are 20 times faster than priority, okay?
那篇帖子实际上对优先级人员造成了困扰，呃，因为你知道，
And that post actually messed up with priority people, uh, because, you know,
在这个世界上，很难做到比另一个基线快20倍，
in the world, it's very hard to be 20 times another baseline,
一定有某些地方没有被正确评估。
There must be something that is not correctly evaluated.
关于modular是否真的比priority快20倍，曾经有过激烈的争论，
And there was a strong debate on if modular is indeed 20 times faster than priority,
如果你在Google上搜索一下，你会发现答案。明白吗？
and if you do some search on Google, you will find it out. Okay?
这两个是主要的编译器，好吗？
These are two main compilers, okay?
呃，我记得四年前，编译器比这还多，但它们都
Uh I think four years ago, there are more compiler than this, but they all
死掉了。只有这四个幸存下来。
died. Only this four survive.
这意味着现在做这个方向的研究并不是个好选择。
Okay? That means it's not a good research to do today.
好的。是的，我不会做编译器方向。
Okay. Yeah, I wouldn't do compiler.
好的。那么，让我们专注于编译器的底层机制，好吗？
Okay. So what is, let's focus on the underlying uh, um, mechanisms for compiler, okay?
今天我们主要会关注算子组合。
So today we are going to focus mostly on operator combination.
这是一个低风险的层次。Uder会在高层次上给你一个算子代码
That is a low risk layer. That is Uder give you a operator code at a high level
通过高层次的定义，我们如何把这段代码编译成低层次的程序，
with a high level definition, how we can compile this code into low level programs,
比如说，Coda内核或者分块矩阵乘法这类代码。
for example, Coda kernels or tiled matm this kind of code.
好吗？我觉得这基本上让你有了一个整体的概念，对吧？
Okay? I think this basically give you a higher idea, right?
所以der会写这种代码，主要只是做声明，并不是为了效率，好吗？
So der write this kind of code, which is mostly just declaration, not for efficiency, okay?
编译器的任务基本上就是，
And the mission of the compiler is basically,
我要处理这段代码。
I'm going to take this piece of code.
我要为你的代码和你的硬件找到最合适的循环结构。
I'm going to find a loop that works best for your code on your hardware.
因为根据循环因子，有很多种循环方式。
Because there are so many ways to loop, depending on the looping factor.
好的。所以最终要归结为为你的硬件找到最合适的循环方式。
Okay. So eventually it boils down into finding the perfect loop for your hardware for
针对这个形状，为操作符做备忘录。
that shape that memo for the operator.
明白了吗？为了做到这一点，
Okay? In order to do this,
我会给你一个工作流程，好吗？
I will give you a workflow, okay?
这里用户写了一个非常简单的代码，就是，这里是A加B等于
So here the user writes a very simple code that is, um this is ready at A plus B equal to
C。但根据ABC的形状以及目标硬件，
C. But depending on the shape of ABC and also the target hardware,
比如说寄存器数量、共享内存数量，
for example, the lumber registers, the lumber shared memory,
你可以生成许多不同版本的这段代码。
you can generate many different versions of this code.
你基本上可以用这种方式进行循环。
You can basically loop in this way.
你也可以用这种方式进行循环。
You can also loop in this way.
我们大概知道它们的区别，因为我无法区分这个层和那个层。
We probably know the difference because I can't tell this layer tell this layer
在不同的存储层级上。
at a different memory hierarchy.
我也可以切换访问方式。
And also, I can switch the access.
我把这个设置为32左右，可能会得到不同的性能表现。
I make this for about this 32 and I will get probably a different performance
这取决于内存层级的容量。
depending on the memory hierarchy capacity.
最终，编译器希望找到最优的循环方式。
And eventually the compiler wants to find the perfect loop
然后基本上会把这种循环进行降级处理。
and then basically lower this kind of loop.
这个循环是在Picon代码里的，
This loop is in Picon code,
我想把这个循环降级成某种内核代码。
I want to lower this loop into some kernel code.
而且所有这些都是自动完成的。
And all this is being done automatically.
好吗？这就是算子编译器的高级概念。
Okay? That is the high level idea of operator compiler.
所以现在你了解了问题，让我们更深入地探讨我们要解决的具体问题。
So now you understand the problem and let's dive deeper on the exact problem we're trying to solve.
如果你想构建这种编译器，我们会遇到很多问题。
So we are ficing a lot of problem if you want to build this kind of compiler.
其中之一是我们需要枚举所有的可能性。
One is and we need to enumerate all the possibilities.
然后问题就是我如何表示所有的可能性。
Then the problem is how I can represent all the possibilities.
或者更具体地说，我如何表示循环，对吧。
Or more concretely how I represent the loops. Right.
我需要表示循环。好的，我需要找到一种表示方法，这样我
I need to represent loops. Okay, I need to find the repreenton so I
就可以基本上在所有的表示空间中进行搜索。
can basically search over all the repenting space.
第二点是，一旦我有了这个循环的表示空间，如何找到接近最优的值。
Second is once I have that repenting space of loops, how to find the close to optimal value.
那我应该遍历四的第一维还是三十二的第二维，还是有别的方法？
Like should I loop over the first dimension of four second dimensthirty two or another way?
我需要，这是一个优化问题。
I need to This is optimiing problem.
对，我有一个空间。
Right I have a space.
我想优化这个空间，可以吗？
I want to optimize that space, okay?
最后，我基本上想加速这个过程，因为我不能
And finally, I want to basically accelerate this process because I cannot
把这个当成一个无解的问题，让我的程序用一辈子去搜索。
put this as unsolvable problem that I have a program that I search over for my entire life.
我想减少搜索空间，并且我想泛化
I want to reduce the search space, and I want to generalize
这种东西从一个设备到另一个设备。
this kind of thing from one device to the other.
比如说，我为GPU甚至H100搜索一个循环。
For example, I search one loop for GPU even hundred.
我还希望这个循环在H100上也能表现得相当好，大概就是这样。
I also want this loop to work reasonably well on H 100, something like that.
好吗？所以有很多种方法可以构建这种编译器，
Okay? So there are many ways to build this kind of compiler,
我将大致介绍一种在当今编译器TVM中采用的方法。
and I'm going to introduce roughly one way that adopted in today's compiler, TVM.
在TVM中，为了解决这个问题，他们的做法是，
Okay? So in TVM, in order to solve this problem, what they do is, uh,
他们首先会定义一个搜索空间。
they will first define the three space.
然后，他们有一些算法，基本上就是在这个空间中导航。
And then, they have some algorithm, which basically what navigated this space.
为什么要枚举所有可能性？因为要根据你的用户代码和目标硬件来决定。
Okay? And why enumerate all the possibility given your user code and, uh, your target hardware.
他们还有一些代码生成器，一旦你确定了一种可能性，比如说，
And they also have some code generator that once you lock down one possibility, for example,
你有一个高层次的循环结构，然后你找到了，
you have a high level repeton with that loop and you figure out,
你要选择的寄存器和循环因子。
the register and the looping factors you try to choose.
另一层会接管这个循环，把那段代码转换成内核代码。
Another layer, we'll take that loop and convert that code into kernel code.
这是编译器中的一个典型问题。
This is a typical problem in compiler.
它被称为代码生成。
It's called code generation.
现在，这可以通过ARM来完成，顺便说一句，但当时是通过，
And today, this can be done by ARMs, by the way, but this was done by,
呃，像手工编码完成的，好吗？
uh, like handcraft coding, okay?
最终你会得到很多数据，这些数据是一个循环和一个编译后的内核，
And eventually you will get a lot of data, which is a loop and a compiled kernel,
你将把这个内核直接应用到你的目标设备上。
you're going to apply this kernel directly into your target device.
这样你就能获得性能提升。
So you'll get a performance.
例如，这个内核将在这个特定芯片上运行100毫秒。
For example, this kernel will run in 100 milliseconds, uh, on this given chip.
所以你会得到所有这些数据对。
So you're going to get all these kind of data pairs.
你可以选择在这里停止。
So you can either stop here.
也就是说，你只需选择表现最好的一个，然后把代码返回给用户，就可以了。
That is, you just pick the best performing one and you return the code to the user, you are good.
或者如果你想生成更多一些，你可以把这个当作机器和训练数据。
Or if you want to generatee a little bit, you can take this as a machine and training data.
好的。X 基本上就是循环。
Okay. The X is basically the loop.
Y 基本上是该循环在目标硬件上的性能。
The Y is basically the performance of that loop on the target hardware.
然后你用这些 XY 对训练神经网络，
And you train these XY pairs into a neural network,
让这个新网络在未来预测，如果你想切换循环的话，
and you let this new network to predict in the future, if you want to switch the loop,
我能获得多少性能提升。
how much performance I would get.
这样一来，一旦我有了这个性能模型，嗯，我基本上可以，
And in this way, once I have this performance model, um, I can basically,
呃，你知道，可以做一些泛化。
uh, you know, generalize a little bit.
比如说当我有不同的形状或者不同的硬件时，
Like s I have a different shape when I have a different hardware,
我可以立即进行推理，并尝试为自己找到完美的循环。
I can immediately do inference and try to get the perfect loop for me.
好吗？这样说有道理吗？
Okay? Does it make sense?
很好。这个叫做Auto TM，呃，它是TM编译器里非常有名的一层。
Cool. And this one is called Auto TM and, uh, it's a very famous layer, uh, in TM compiler, y.
但是在这里，你大致可以了解这个工作流程，但其实还有很多很多问题。
But here, uh, you roughly get the idea of this workflow, but there are still many many problems.
为什么要表示循环呢？
Why is actually represent loops.
好吗？表示循环的一种方式其实是，
Okay? One way to represent the loop is basically,
呃，我们仍然需要专家来写很多模板。
uh, we still need experts to write a lot of templates.
好吗？所以我们只需要请一些专家来写这个模板。
Okay? So we just ask some expert to write this template.
比如说，这是我们为com 2D做的一个循环，我们
For example, this is a loop we did for com two D and we are going
要请这些专家生成很多很多这种版本的循环。
to ask this experts to generate many, many of these versions loops.
但是我们把这个循环因子作为一个占位符，然后让我们的编译器自动找出
But we leave this looping factor as a placeholder, and we let our compiler to automatically find out
用于填充这个循环因子的具体数值。
the values to fill this value into looping factor.
然后我就可以回到这个工作流程，对吧？
And then I can go back to this workflow, right?
另一个问题是，一旦我有了这种循环模板，我该如何操作
Um the other problem is once I have this kind of looping templates, how do I basically navigate
这个空间，并尝试以最快的方式搜索最优解，对吧？
the space and try to search for the optimal answer, right, in the fast possible way.
有几种方法。一种是，这其实是一个典型的搜索问题，对吧？
There are a few ways. One is, this is a typical search problem, right?
比如说，我有一个循环模板，我想尝试一下。
So say, I have one looping template, which I want to try.
我的做法是，每次把一些建议的数值填入这个循环中，
What I do is basically every time I fill some proposed values into this loop,
然后我可以直接评估这个部分循环，尝试获得一些性能指标。
and I can go directly evaluate this partial loop and try to get some performance indicator.
如果这个性能已经很差，
And if this performance is already pretty bad,
基本上，我可以根据这个循环来修剪下一个可能的构建方式。
I can basically prune the next possibilities build based on top of this looping.
我会做一些回溯，或者进行一些其他的搜索实现，最终我可以，嗯，
I do some backtracking or do some whatever search opplementation, and eventually I can, um,
得到一个相当不错的循环用于内核实现。
get a reasonably good loop for the kernel implementation.
好的。同样地，正如我之前解释的那样，
Okay. And similarly, as I already explained,
我也可以用我的历史数据构建一些成本模型，
I can also build some cost model using my historical data,
但我无法预测这个循环在目标硬件或形状上表现会好还是坏。
and I can't predict if this loop is going to do well or bad on this target hardware or shape.
是的。所以我们基本上有两种方式来构建这些竞争者。
Yeah. So it's two ways that we can basically build these kind of competors.
好的，有什么问题吗？
Okay, any question?
有。
Yeah.
基本上，我认为没有现成的求解器可以解决这个问题。
It's basically, I don't think there's track solver to solve this.
这基本上是指数级的复杂，好吗？
This is basically exponentially, uh, complex, okay?
所以在编译器领域的人们，他们会尝试构建各种
And so people in Compiler computer, they just try to build all kinds of
搜索算法来剪枝可能性，并尽快找到解决方案。
searching algorithms to prune the possibilities and try to locate the solution as fast as possible.
但我想指出的一点是，一旦你找到了这个解决方案，你就没问题了，对吧？
But one thing I want to note is once you locate the solution, uh, then you are good, right?
因为对于那个特定的算子和硬件，
Because for that particular operator and hardware,
你已经找到了一个非常不错的实现方式，
you already find a pretty good decent implementation,
并且你可以在以后的运行中一直保留这段代码。
and you can keep that code forever in the future runs.
其次，在大多数情况下，这比让专家手动工程实现要好。
Second is, in most cases, this is better than letting experts doing the engineering.
因为对于这种搜索，你要做的就是开发一个搜索算法，然后让它
Because for this kind of search, what you do is you develop a search algorithm and you just pull
跑一个月或者一周，最终它会给你返回一个结果。
it run for one month or one week and eventually it will return something for you.
但是如果让人类来开发这个，会花更长时间，对吧？是的。
But if you the human to develop that, that will take even longer, right? Yeah.
一个是人为错误，另一个是机器工时。
One is human error, the other is machine hour.
嗯，好的。这基本上就是我们进行编译操作的一个高层次思路。
Yeah. Okay. Yeah, that is basically a high level idea of how we do operate compilation.
简单总结一下，我们需要找到一种方式，用可能性来表示循环空间。
To summarize a little bit, we need to find a way to represent the loop space by possibilities.
我们还需要确保搜索空间能很好地覆盖
And we need to basically, make sure the search space have a good coverage
常见的优化方式，比如分块，等等。
of common ogmentations, like tailing, whatever.
我们还需要构建一个高效的搜索算法，来遍历整个空间。
And we need to build a efficient search algorithm to navigate all the entire space.
我们还需要有一个评估指标，来判断这个循环好不好。
And we also need to have a evaluation metric that tell if this loop is good or not.
好的，好的。
Okay. Okay.
那回到这个问题，我要给你一个问题，让你思考一下。
Then coming back to this, I'm going to give you a question so you can think about that.
好的，就像我刚才说的，机加工编译的前提基本上是
Okay. So like I said, yeah, like I said, so the premise of machining compilation is basically
我们尝试自动生成代码的最优配置
we try to automatically generate optimal configurations that code
给用户提供机加工代码和目标软件。
giving users machining code and targetware.
我的疑问是，你认为机加工编译器实现了这个目标吗？
And my question is, do you think, machining compiler is achieving this goal?
我来发表一下我的看法，我认为没有。
I will offer opinion, I don't think so.
我会给你有力的证据。
I will give you strong evidence.
为什么？我们知道现在大多数语言模型都是通过Flash Attention训练的。
Why? We know that most of today's language model are trained by flash attention.
编译器是由Flash Attention发明的吗，对吧？
Compiler was invented by flash attention, right?
就像我说的，人们在2018到2021年间做编译器研究。
Like I said, people doing compiler research during 2018 and 2021.
Flash Attention是在2022年发布的。
Flash attention was released in 2022.
And it was handcrafted by a guy called
Trida who is a principal Princeton professor today.
Then I ask the question, I will leave this to you.
Why compiler didn't discover the flash attention?
Right? Because theoretically, if your compiler is smart enough and your compiler
can search the entire space, it should be able to search for flight engine.
But eventually, we ended up with someone actually implementing flight engine using
their own manual engineering.
I will leave this question to you.
But I'm not saying that compiler has no contribution because I
我认为确实有很多今天更简单的操作，比如说，元M卷积，
think indeed many many today's other simpler operations, for example, met M convolution,
编译器领域的人们确实构建了一些非常优秀的，
compiler people indeed, build some really good, uh,
内核，这些内核人类可能无法理解，但却能在GPU上高效运行。
kernels that human probably is not able to understand, but rather performing on GPUs. Okay.
好的，这就是一个非常快速的操作符编译器介绍。
Okay, that is a pretty fast, introduction operator compiler.
我想下周我们会再回到这个话题，我们将讨论图编译器。
I think next week we are coming back to this again, and we are going to talk about graph compiler.
也就是如何自动转换图结构。
That is how to transform graphs automatically.
好吗？那我们现在进入本次讲座的第三部分。
Okay? So let's move to the third part of this lecture.
在第三部分，我想介绍一种稍微不同的方法，
And in the third part, I want to introduce a little bit on a different approach,
好的，这种方法基本上是对待……
okay, which is basically treating.
非常有名的方法，对吧？那么是哪种方法呢？
Very famous one, right? So which treating?
所以我们有很多种treating。为什么是这个treating，对吧？
So we have many treatings. Why is this treating, right?
我们现在说的不是这个treating。好吧，这是我们自己。
We are not talking this treating. Okay, this is us.
还有另一个非常让人困惑的lamin treating。
And there's another very confusing lamin treating.
它叫做NVIDIA Treating推理服务器。
It's called NVIDIA Treating inference server.
如果你在WDA网站上搜索这个，会发现它是一个开源项目。
And if you search this on WDA website, it's there's open source project.
我们现在也不是在说这个。
We are also not talking about this one.
这个是用来服务transformers的，我们稍后会讲到它，
This one is for serving transformers and we are going to talk about this little bit later,
但这不是我们现在要讲的treating。
but this is not the treatment we'll talk about.
我们基本上是在说这个treating。
We are basically talking about this treating.
这是open treating，好吗？那什么是treating？
This is open treating, okay? So what is treating?
我们介绍了Koda，也介绍了自动编译器。
Um, we introduced Koda we introduced the automatic compiler.
我想你应该能明白这个意思。
I think you'll get the idea.
所以我们基本上可以把它们分为两个极端，Koda在左边。
So we can basically put them into two extremes, Koda on the left.
Koda被定义为一种特定设备的DSL，领域专用语言。
And Koda is defined as a device specific DSL, domain specific language.
好吗？这基本上是媒体为你提供的编程设备的方法。
Okay? It's basically the way that media provides for you to program the devices.
编译器则是另一个极端。
Compiler is other extreme.
那么Koda的优缺点是什么？
So what is pros and cons of Koda?
Koda的优点基本上是开发者可以随心所欲地做任何事情，对吧？
The pros of Koda is basically developers can do whatever the heck they want, right?
他们可以把性能发挥到极致，只要你
Uh, they can squeeze the last bit of performce as long as you are
是一个强大的Koda程序员，你就可以做到。
a powerful Koda programmer, you can do that.
它给你带来了各种可能性，对吧？
It gives you all the sort of possibilities, right?
你可以用任何你想用的数据结构，而不是Koda内核。
You can use whatever data structure you want instead of Koda kernel.
但是Koda的缺点是什么？
But what is the cons of Koda?
缺点是一样的。
The const is the same.
开发者可以随心所欲地做任何事情。
Developer can do whatever heck they want.
这也意味着如果我不是Koda程序员，那就需要很深的专业知识，
Which also means that if I'm not a Koda programmer, then it requires deep expertise,
而且性能优化非常耗时，正如你所看到的。
and the performance optim is very time consuming, as you can see.
当我给你一段quota代码时，
When I give you a piece of quota code,
我需要解释很多内容。
I have to explain a lot.
你必须把你的思维方式转变成SIMD，并且你在这方面要非常擅长。
You have to convert your brain to SIMD, and you have to be very good at that in
为了交付一份好的代码。
order to deliver a piece of good code.
明白了吗？你可以想象代码库
Okay? And you can imagine the code base with
Koda 非常混乱，因为你要把很多东西加到 CP 代码里，
Koda is very messy because you are going to add a lot of this into into CP code and
你的 Quota 代码在另一个文件里，然后那个 CP 代码会启动那个内核。
you Quota code in another file and that CP code will launch that kernel.
你需要两个不同的编译器。
You need two different compilers.
一个是 CPP 编译器，另一个是 Koda 编译器。
One is the CPP compiler and the other is Koda compiler.
顺便说一句，Koda 编译器其实很慢。
Koda compiler is pretty slow by the way.
好的。那么我们回到这个自动编译器上来。
Yeah. Okay. Then let's go back to this automatic compiler.
那么自动编译器的优缺点是什么？
So what is the pros and cons of automatic compiler?
对开发者来说迭代非常快，因为你只需要用 Python 写高级代码，然后
Very fast iteration for developers, because you just write your high level code in Python and
你装饰了Toch Compel，一切看起来都很好，对吧？
you decorate Toch Compel and things are good, right?
你可以很快地提出想法，并交给编译器处理。
You can pull up ideas quickly and give it to compiler.
但问题是，它无法表达某些类型的想法。
But the problem, it cannot represent certain types of ideas.
我已经举过一个例子了。
And I already give an example.
编译器没有发现Flash attention，因为在搜索空间中，
Flash attention was not discovered by compilers because in a search space,
对于Flash attention来说，并没有这样的重复性。
there is no such repetition for flash attention.
明白了吗？而且你也不能使用Cosmo数据结构。
Okay? And also, you cannot use Cosmo data structures.
在编译器中，最终还是会归结为你想要生成代码的问题，
And in compiler will indeed boil down to be a problem that you want to generate code,
而代码生成是传统编译器中的一个老问题，
and code generation is old problem in the old compiler traditional compiler,
这是一个非常困难的问题。
which is a very difficult problem.
我认为编程语言和编译器领域的人们，他们
I think programming language and compiler people they are
已经做了很多很多年了，好吗。
doing this a lot of many, many years, okay.
好的，这基本上可以帮助你理解什么是treating。
Okay, that basically help you understand where treating is.
好的，所以treating大致处于中间位置，对吧？
Okay. So treating is roughly in the middle, okay?
它是一种领域特定语言，但它是基于Python的。
It is a domain spec language, but it is Python based.
另一方面，它不是自动的，但它也可以手动，在bacon中，
On the other hand, it's not automatic, but it also well, manually, in the bacon,
treating会帮助你优化一些东西。
treating will help you optimize some things.
比如说，自动帮你做tiling。
For example, telling it do telling for you.
你不需要自己写tiling代码。
You don't have to write your own telling.
好的？所以基本上它试图在纯领域特定语言之间找到一个平衡点，
Okay? So basically it trying to strike a balance between pure domain speak language,
纯自动编译器就在中间。
and the pure automatic compaer it's in the middle.
好的，这里我基本上放了四个标志，你可以看到，
Okay. And here I basically put four logos and you can see,
我觉得这四个标志太像了。
I feel these four logos are so similar.
一定是同一个设计师做的。对吧，好吧。
It must come from the same designer. Yeah. Okay.
好的。那么说到产品定位，基本上，我们做的事情比Koda简单，
Yeah. Okay. So treating speech is basically, how about we do something that is simpler than Koda,
但比自动编译器更贵。
but more expensive than automatic compilers.
但和Koda比，我们更便宜，但比图形编译器更复杂。
But compared to Coda, we are less expensive, but we are more complicated than graph compilers.
这基本上就是我们的市场定位。
And this is basically treating market piece.
好吗？我觉得这个说法太抽象了，因为对于一个
Okay? I think this is way too abstract because it's very hard for a person or
没有相关经验的人或者工程师来说，很难理解这个定位。
engineer with no experience on this, understand this pitch.
但事实证明这个方法非常成功。
But it turns out this is super successful.
如果时间允许的话，我们会讲两个程序，
And we are going to go through if time permits, we are going to go through two programs,
但我觉得时间不够，所以我们只讲一个程序。好的。
but I don't think we have time, so we are going to go through one program. Okay.
在处理用户自定义的张量时，
So, in treating, uh, the user defined tensors in RAM.
Treaton 给你提供了一个基本上是原生 Python 的语言。
Okay? So treaton gives you a language that is basically Python native.
它在 PySon 中实现了自己的程序接口。
It embody its own like a program interface in PySon.
所以写 Treaton 基本上就等同于写 Python。
So writing treating is basically equivalent to writing Python.
而且 Treaton 还给你提供了很多来自 torch 的原语。
Okay. And also treatments give you so many primitives that is basically from torch.
比如说，如果你想写点什么，你可以用 torch 的索引操作，
For example, if you want to write something, you can use torch indexing operations,
你可以用 torch 提供给你的任何东西，非常直观，对吧？
you can use whatever torch offers to you, which is super intuitive, okay?
但是这种处理方式也会带来一些限制。
But the treatment also give you a few limitations.
比如说，当你分配数组时，数组的形状必须是2的幂。
For example, when you allocate arrays, it has to be a shape of power too.
这是因为在后端，处理会进行一些调整，
That is because in the back end, the treating will do some telling,
自动为你做一些组织。
do some organization for you automatically.
所以必须以这种方式进行限制。
So it has to restrict in this way.
明白了吗？那我们来看一个处理的例子。
Okay? So here, let's go say one example treating
在这个例子中，我们正在处理数组 eight。
Here in this one, we are doing array eight.
它等于 X 加 Y。
They equal to X plus Y.
好，现在我让你们看这段代码30秒。
Okay, I'm going to let you look at this for 30 seconds.
好，我们来试着解析这段代码。
Okay, let's try to parse this code.
嗯，这样看这段代码会好很多，对吧？
Um, it's much better to look at this code, right?
这看起来很熟悉，对吧？就像perch一样。
This is so familiar, right? Like perch.
我觉得你第一印象就是觉得这是Python。
I think the first impression you had is it is Python.
是啊，写起来简单多了。
Yeah, so much easier to write.
好吧？你注意到的第二点是我有这个。
Okay? The second thing you noticed is I have this one.
Treating do JT和torch非常相似，
Treating do JT is very similar to torch,
和compel或者其他Jet的竞品都差不多。
Do compel or any other Jet competitor.
所以treating确实是Jet的一个竞品，好吗？
So treating is indeed a Jet competitor, okay?
而且我基本上用的是PySon的语法。
And I basically use the grammar of PySon.
我定义了一个函数。
I define a function.
嗯，我给它一些，比如说数组。
Uh, I give it a few, um, like arrays.
但在triton中，所有的数组都是指向张量的指针。
But in triton, all the arrays are pointers to a tensor.
明白吗？这和Python有点不同，因为在Python里你得到的是对象，对吧？
Okay? This is slightly different from Python because in pyson you get object, right?
但在triton里是指向数组的指针。
But in triton is a pointer to array.
这意味着它是一个内存地址，明白吗？
Which means it's a memory address, okay?
而且triton的内核基本上会被映射到单个块上。
And the treating kernels will basically be mapped to a single block.
这也是为什么Triton可以稍微简化UDA的原因。
And this is also why Triton can simplify UDA a little bit.
因为在CUDA中，你必须定义你的块形状，对吧。
Because in CUDA, you have to define your block shape, right.
你还要定义你的网格形状，也就是你想用多少个块。
You also you define your grid shape that is how many blocks you want to use.
然后你定义你的线程块形状，也就是你想用多少个线程。
And then you define your thread block shape, that is how many threads you want to use.
所以你需要以类似两级层次结构的方式来思考这个问题。
So you have to think in this kind of like a two level hierarchy.
但在Triton中，这个过程被稍微简化了一些。
But in Triton, it was simplified a little bit.
也就是说，你只需要考虑一件事，就是你要思考如何
That is you only think about one thing that is you think about how to
编写一个会被映射到一个块上的程序。
write a program that will be mapped to one block.
也就是说，很多很多线程会读取一个块。
That is many many reads a block.
而在这个内核之外，你要做的是定义一个由不同块组成的网格，
And outside of this kernel, what do you do you define a grade with different blocks
Triton会自动将其映射到块和线程上。
and treating will automatically map this into blocks and threads.
明白了吗？这已经在一定程度上简化了我们的思考方式，因为就像我说的，
Okay? This already simplified the way we think a little bit because like I said,
当你编写这段代码时，你只需要考虑如何让它在
when you write this piece of code, you only think about how to make it run
很多很多线程上运行，而不是在块上运行。
on many many threads, not blocks.
好的。这里我们通过这个，然后就结束今天的讲座，好吗？
Okay. And here, let's pass this and we'll finish lecture, okay?
这里我调用了一个叫做treating EPA的接口，也就是range，这个API和tort里的非常相似。
So here, I call a treating EPA which is range, and this is a very similar API
也就是说我要创建一个从0到123的数组，对吧？
from tort that is I'm going to create rate 0-123, right?
你会注意到，每当你在treating里创建某些东西时，
One thing you'll notice that whenever you create something in treating,
如果你用的是这个包里的东西，它会被创建在SRAM上。
using something start from this package, it was created on SRAM.
好的，那是所有流处理器线程共享的内存。
Okay. That is a shared memory of all the threads in the streaming i processor.
你要记住这段代码只会被单个block启动一次。
You'll remember this code is going to be launched just one single block.
所以你创建了这个数组，在SRAM上，这是一个偏移数组。
So you create this array, um SRM This is offset array.
然后你要做的，就是用Python的API来操作指针语义。
And then what you do is, uh, you try to manipulate the pointer semantics using Python API.
所以这里我有了我的XYZ的起始地址，对吧？
So here I have the starting address of my XYZ, right?
当我尝试编写这个程序时，
And when I try to write this program,
我需要考虑如何确保每个线程都处理一部分X加Y等于零的情况。
I need to think about how I make sure each thread is skewed a part of X plus Y equal to zero.
所以这里我把它分配到26或24个线程中。
So here I launch it into 26 or 24 threads.
基本上，这个块里的每个线程，我们都需要让它处理一个元素a，对吧？
So basically, each thread in that block, we need to take one element a, right?
所以我的想法是，
So what I do is my hello idea is,
我要确保每个线程读取一个元素。
I'm trying to make sure each thread read one element.
从HPM到SRM。
From HPM to SRM.
这就是协作式获取，对吧？
That is cooperative fetching, right?
然后我会让每一行来进行计算。
And then I'm going to let each road to take the competition.
也就是说，我让每一行读取两个元素A和B，然后把它们加在一起，合并起来。
That is I read achrod read two elements A and B, and then add them together and get together
然后把结果写回到C中，明白了吗？
results and then write the results back into C. Okay?
这是一段纯SMD代码。
And this this is a pure SMD code.
好的，我基本上要做的是
Okay. So what I do is basically
我首先在我的SRAM上创建这个语义点的偏移量，
I first create this point of semantics that is offset on my SRAM and
还有你会注意到，在Cuda中你需要进行一些协作式的数据获取。
um and one thing you'll notice that in Cuda, you have to do some cooperative fetching.
但在这里，你只需要调用Christ API，它会自动映射到1024个线程。
But here, you just go Christ API and this will be automatically mapped to 1024 threads.
这意味着这一行代码会以SMD方式在这么多线程中执行。
Which means this line is going to be executed SMD in that many threads.
然后我会把这个偏移量加到每个指针上。
Then I'm going to add this offset to each pointer.
这就是加法操作。
This is the add operation.
而在treating中，treating基本上会处理这些行并使
And in treating, treating will basically take care of the lines and make
确保每个线程块都会对偏移量执行一次加法操作。
sure each threading that block will perform one add on the offset.
一旦我有了这个偏移量，我就知道了，
And once I have this offset, I know,
我需要把元素从HPM加载到我的SRM，处理基本上会给你
I need to load the element from HPM to my SRM, treating will basically give you
另一个叫做TL load的EPL。
another EPL called TL load.
这个加载操作也是，嗯，主动预取的，对吧？
And this load is also, um, coptive fetching, right?
因为处理会自动把这个节点映射到不同的读取操作中。
Because the treatment will automatically map this node into different reads.
但我们如何让每个写操作加载到准确的元素呢？
But how we tell each right to load the exact element.
我们告诉它们的方法其实就是给它们X PTRs，记得吗
The way we tell that is basically we give them the X PTRs Remember
这个X PR是以这样一种方式生成的，对于每个元素，
this X PR was generated in a way where for each element,
我都会应用一个不同的偏移量。
I apply a different offset.
所以每次读取基本上对应一个元素，并尝试读取它。
So each read will basically corresponds to one element and try to read it
一个对应的元素来自XN Y。
a corresponding element from XN Y.
这个X和Y，基本上就是分配的RM。
And this X and Y, basically, the uh, RM allocated.
最终，我会进行一次竞争。
And eventually, I'm going to do a competition.
这段代码依然是向量化的，但处理会自动
And this is still vectorize the code, but the treatment will automatically
把它映射到很多很多线程中。
map this into many many threads.
所以每个读取只计算它自己对应的元素。
So each read only compute its own corresponding element.
这个结果就在那个线程的寄存器里，对吧。
And this result was in the register of that thread, right.
最终，我会把这个结果存回Z指针里。
And eventually, I'm going to store this result back into the Z pointer.
那我怎么知道每个线程该把结果写到哪个位置呢？
And I know why each thread knows which position to write the results?
因为PTR实际上就是PTR加上偏移量，而且我已经为每个线程应用了偏移量。
Because the PTRs are basically PTR plus offset and I already apply the offset for each thread.
好的。是的，这基本上是我们处理代码的第一步。
Okay. Yeah, that's basically our first piece of treating code.
你可以看到，用户只需要负责映射。
And you can see, user will only be responsible for mapping.
在这个内核之外，用户负责创建
At outside of this kernel, user is responsible for creating
不同的块并传递到内核中。
different blocks and passes into the kernel.
但在这个内核内部，用户的像salt这样的处理过程已经被简化了。
But inside of this kernel, the users like salt process are already being simplified.
我只需要考虑会被映射到所有线程的高层代码，而不再需要考虑块了。
I only need to think about high rat code that will be mapped to all threats but not blocks anymore.
并且所有的代码，
And all the code,
API基本上都是基于Python的，你可以从torch中调用许多类似的API。
APS are basically Python based, and you can co many many similar APS from torch.
好吗？今天我大致就讲这些。
Okay? Yeah, that's pretty much all I have today.
在下一节课中，我们会继续在Triden上完善这个程序。
And in the next lecture, we are going to continue grand this program on triden a little bit. Yeah.